Yorlisoning to ancient faithradio.com.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by
spirits, angels, demons, and saints.
In our time, many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism,
to see and to know reality as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like?
How do we engage with it well?
How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick, and Father Stephen De Young
host this live Colin show focused on enchantment in creation.
the union of the scene and unseen as made by God and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Good evening, giant killers, dragon slayers, goblin cleavers, imp impellers.
You are listening to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
And my co-host, the very Reverend Doctor, Stephen D. Young, is with me from Lafayette, Louisiana.
And I'm Father-Industinivandamic in Emmaus, Pennsylvania.
and we are live.
And if you're listening to us live, you can call us at 855-237-2346, just like the voice
of Steve will keep reminding you throughout this program, and you can talk to us.
And we'll get your calls in the second half of the show, and our very own Matushka Trudy
will be taking those calls.
This episode is sponsored by our friends at the Orthodox Studies Institute at St. Constantine
college which exists to advance the study and application of Orthodox Christianity
faithfulness to holy tradition. OSI is offering online courses this fall, including a five-week course on the book of Ina,
I feel like there should be some kind of reverb for that. Tought by Father Steven DeYoung. You can learn about the courses and you can
register at orthodoxstudies.com slash LOS and if you register using that link, you'll get a free copy of Father Steven's book
apocrypha an e-book of that book from ancient faith published
and registration is now open. It's coming up quick, everybody.
So, Trigger, yeah.
I will continue to pronounce it Enic.
Enic?
A sleastak.
Not sleastak?
Folks will be confounded.
That's true. You do say it.
You just got to know going in. I'm going to say first, Enic, and you're going to be like,
what?
Yeah.
Well tonight...
We're not talking about the book of Enoch.
Contrary to what you might have heard.
Yet.
That's true.
We're talking about the resurrection of the body.
This is a central and critical dogma of Christianity that often is strangely overlooked
or even forgotten.
Yet the scriptures tell us that all of mankind will be raised from the dead at the voice of
the Son of God at his second and glorious appearing.
But what does it mean that we will be raised?
The resurrection mean that the same
set of atoms that we're carrying around right now, we're persistent to the age to come.
No.
Oh, sorry.
Good night everybody.
Go ahead.
It's okay.
We'll even persist into next week.
Oh, sorry.
Who is not so good?
Who is the you or the I that's going to be raised?
I mean, and what does this mean about salvation?
So since a lot of people think that the Christian afterlife consists solely, see what I did there,
there of what happens to the soul.
So we start there.
If the soul is me, then why does my body even have to be raised?
Like what is even going on with that?
Yeah.
So that's play to brain.
Oh.
Like stuffing your skull with a little play to.
Yes.
That's what happens when you read too much play to.
Let him ruin your metaphysics.
Before we jump into the topic at hand.
Oh.
Is this a rant or a...
This is a mini-rad.
sort of a follow up on last episode.
Uh oh.
Because it has come to my attention that there's some people out there who are unhappy with
our brief discussion of open thism.
Oh yes, it's true.
Uh, last time.
And so, uh, I'm going to briefly discuss it some more.
Oh man.
Uh, those folks are probably going to be equally unhappy with this.
or even more. But because you know we had really discussed talking that much about
Open Theism. We talked about sort of it passing. Yeah, it's not it was not really the
topic of the show. And some people felt like you know maybe I was putting too much
process theology into it to much haggle on it. That was me trying to steal man the
position.
That was me trying to present it as better than it actually is.
But so since people didn't like that, I'm going to talk about how it actually is.
So open the is of doesn't make any sense.
It literally makes no sense.
even go there you have to accept a bunch of
fall spree suppositions like God is a being like other beings. God exists within time.
Right. The biggest piece there I think. Yes, both of which mean God is finite. So already we're
dealing with, you know, a pagan God, not the true God. But for the sake of argument, right?
Let's assume that these things were true. The statement, God doesn't know the future because
the future doesn't exist yet.
Okay, that is not a coherent sense.
That sense does not make any sense,
and it does not communicate anything.
The future doesn't exist yet, is in coherent.
Because the future is not a thing.
The future is the present, plus a finite amount of motion.
Right?
It's not like all the things that exist now
are going to cease to
exist a second from now and be replaced by a whole set of new things. What kind of bizarre
ontology is that? Right? So, forgot not to know the future. Since the future is just the
present plus a finite amount of motion. Despite the fact that God intimately knows everything
he's created. And those that's complete past history, he has to have no idea in what
direction that motion will continue in the next five minutes or ten minutes or
twenty minutes. Let me put a finer point on this, okay? My wife can do a pretty good
job of predicting what I'm gonna do tomorrow and predicting what I'm gonna do in
various situations, okay? God knows me far more intimately than my wife as my
creator and you're gonna tell me he has
Oh clue what I'm gonna do.
None.
Zero idea.
So, Opathy isn't required,
not just that, oh God is a giant human,
like the pagans have,
but he's a giant human who's particularly dumb.
Okay, the God of Opathy isn't as inferior to pagan gods.
Cause pagan gods could at least figure out
what would probably happen the next day.
I mean, do you know how many coffees are the religion of the apostles are being thrown against the wall right now if others here?
Hopefully none!
Because if you got through that book and enjoyed it, it's still an open piece, something with...
There was a disconnect!
Okay, there's a disconnect!
That makes no sense!
Okay.
And I know the intent is to preserve free will.
Okay, that's what you're trying to do. You're trying to preserve for-
will by saying God doesn't know what I'm gonna do. But what kind of free will is that? That's not free
will. That's the idea that people act in completely arbitrary ways. In completely nonsensical ways
immune to a chain of cause and effect. So like for God to not know what I'm gonna do tomorrow, it has
to be like equally likely that I will spend the day praying and then I will go build a bomb and blow
all of a stuckeys, right?
Like, who knows what I-
gonna do tomorrow because I have free will. I could just wake up and you know,
decide to throw dishes around the house for 20 minutes, right? Like, who knows what, right?
That's absurd. That's not free will. Are you with the people behave randomly? It's not free will,
right? And that's what would be required for open-theans to preserve free will. So,
And a rant about open theism. You guys brought it on yourself.
You could have just let what we said last time pass, but no.
You thought we did go into it enough. We thought we didn't represent your property.
Properly, well there you go.
So, open theism, grave heresy teaches a different God than the God of Christianity.
Hope you're happy.
Friends, don't let friends.
Become open theist.
So now onto our topic, the bodily resurrection.
Yes. Yes. Yes. How about that? My apologies, Deitywood, it works at a Stuckies. That was not a threat.
Your dates are safe. The bunch of open theist at Stuckies that are calling their managers.
Yeah. Let's see what it's used to not go to work tomorrow that feel free to play that clip over the phone or something and get out of work.
Thank you.
So yeah, so the sort of rhetorical questions,
the conversation starters that you gave there
before my digression.
I felt that they were very well written.
What a great provocative.
I mean, at least one of them I feel like you've used
three times before on this show.
But look, we've got 300 hours.
It was so great.
It was a great break.
I'm going to say a couple things more than once.
Okay, but I mean you're you're you're saying your prank?
about how well you wrote them.
Like has anyone actually counted the number of times
we've said the word right on the year?
Someone should.
Someone will now, you know.
Well, they need to tell us privately
and then we'll have a contest.
It'll be like guessing how many like,
jujubees are in the jar.
They'll sit there with a clicker, you know?
Yeah.
During every episode.
We have people guess, you know,
closest without going over prices, right rules.
You'll win something.
Oh man.
Right? So you were talking about the tendency people have due to Plato brain to associate
the soul with identity. And we've talked about this before. We had did an episode called
Who Stole the Soul? About the Soul. What were we talking about? The Soul. And so of course,
Tonight we're talking about the bodily resurrection through we talking more about.
bodies but we need to revisit the distinction here a little bit because a lot of us have
had this Plato idea fed into us that yourself who you are, the you is your soul and your
body is a husk or a vehicle or something your soul uses to move around that you're the
ghost in the machine.
tour. We're all just big mechs. Yeah, I would have a much cooler machine.
And so all of that, all of that, that is Plano, that is not Christianity, that is
not the Hebrew Scriptures, that's not what a soul is. So as we've talked about
before soul, that is Shin Hebrew literally means life right it means life.
So the soul is the life of an animate. That's where the word animate comes from,
Anima which means soul and land, of an animate creature. And the soul is the life of
a human, the soul is the life of the human body. It is what makes the human body
alive. So it is not the self, it is not the inner person.
It is not the person.
In any sense, it is that element of life that makes your body alive, right?
Because your body is made up of otherwise inert elements and compounds.
Right?
It's a big pile of chemicals that is made alive by something and that's something is the
all.
Right. What was the the quip in that one episode from?
Was it the first season of next generation ugly bags of mostly water?
Yeah. Yeah.
Um, yeah.
So it's what animates literally, right, the body.
But all human souls are essentially the same.
Oh man. You're going to you're going to offend a whole bunch of people with that
one. Well there you go.
That's the soul as such, a human soul as such is a human soul.
Right?
The distinctives of identity do not apply to a human soul.
Meaning I'm not alive in a different sense than Father Andrew.
Right.
The animating principle of my body is not different than the animating principle of his body,
or any of our listeners' bodies.
Right. It is different than the animating principle of animal bodies. Right. And so I said
all human souls are essentially the same. Right. But it is not different from human person
to human person. Right. And when we say that physical death, the physical
death of anything.
really, but including a human, is the separation of the soul from the body. We're not talking about
like two planks that have been nailed together, right, or like your soul is like your emotions and
your feelings, whatever those are, and your thoughts and your mind and then your body is just like
tissue. We're talking about the life leaving your body.
your body is still there, right?
Now it's no longer alive.
And pretty much immediately after the life leaves your body,
all those chemical processes stop, processes stop.
And those elements and compounds start to break down
into an animate matter.
Yeah.
Right?
That's what happens.
So...
Soul being separated from the body, though we've jargonized it a little, is a very little
literal description for what happens when you watch something die.
You watch the life leave it.
Physically materially, everything that was there before is still there now, but it is no
longer alive.
And that thing that
is now gone, that life that is now gone is the thing that we call the soul. So this is
obviously going to be important when we come around, eventually, guess what, it's going
to be the third half to the bodily resurrection, right, which is going to be involved the soul
going back into the body. Right. That being restored. But this
Soil itself has nothing of identity.
And you can see this.
There are obviously examples where you can see this,
Plato and lots of other pagan folks
in different parts of the world
believe in sort of direct reincarnation.
So someone, something dies,
that soul departs from the body
because they're looking at the-
soul as a thing and then it gets another body, right? But even for the completely
platobrained person who believes in reincarnation, that new body, that new person, right, is
not the same person as the old person. Yeah.
There's not a persistence of self. Right. There's clearly some kind of major alteration at
very least within that paradigm.
So they can...
believe it's the same soul, it's the same life that passed from one person to another,
but the self clearly didn't, right? They don't have the memories, they don't have the
same personality, they don't have the, they might be in a different part of the world, right?
Everything may be different, right? So this is part of the idea of this, even if you believe
reincarnation of that kind of thing, the soul isn't the self. Right?
So then we have to move now to the body.
So if your soul isn't yourself, that means yourself, your identity, who you are.
If it doesn't have anything to do with your soul, because your soul is just like every other humans.
Then that means that it has something to do with your body.
Alright, that's something to do with the
other part of that equation.
And this again is something that we as humans instinctively
recognize, especially about other humans,
but not just about other humans.
We recognize that when a person dies
and we're looking at their body, that is still them.
People don't watch a loved one die and then just turn around and shrug and go, okay, well they're gone or you know
It just leave the body where it lays
Like an example that
Well, I have children I have minor children, you know the phrase he hit me
What are you gonna say he didn't hit you?
He hit the fleshly rapper that the real you is inside
You know or is controlling this and sublinging my arms and
That's right no like you know
People know if you get hit you hit me.
Yeah.
And, you know, just to double down and it's you that hit me not the shell, you know, not
your Mac that hit my Mac, you know.
Right.
Yeah.
We would never look at a little bit of just saying, oh, their body died.
I mean, even, even like think about all the things in law as well.
in which the body is very much assumed to be the person.
You know, imagine trying to argue in front of a judge,
oh, I didn't, you know, I didn't shoot him.
I just shot his fleshly form, you know, or whatever.
Yes, yeah, yeah, that's just logical.
And this isn't just based on some kind of developed
philosophy of the body that we now have in the modern era,
Right.
And we know this because you can go all the way back to the Neolithic period as we're
want to do on this show, especially in the first half.
You can go to Chetelhoiaque, you can go to these earliest sites of human civilization on
Earth that we've discovered.
And you find, guess what, they're burying their dead.
They're not abandoning the bodies, so they're loved ones.
They're not getting rid of them, they're not burning them.
they're burying them and not only were they burying them.
them in these early settlements, a family would bury their departed loved ones in the floor of their house.
They would keep those bodies near them and with them.
Right?
Which shows that even back then before a
word of the Bible was written before
Right God revealed himself to Abraham
him before any of that right before there's any promise of
Resurrection recorded in Scripture.
People recognized instinctually
Right that the body of their departed loved one was still their loved one was still that person
That that body was not just the person while they were alive as father Edris pointed out
But even after their dead it continues to be them even when the soul is gone the life is gone. That's still them
Yeah, right. Is it that them packed up and left?
And this is their old house.
Right.
Is there right?
So things like cremation, things like Zoroastrian burial,
these are all practices that develop in certain specific
pagan cultures, mostly after the axiilage,
meaning mostly.
circa 500 BC and later.
And those practices as opposed to burial,
are practices that are based in sort of developed philosophies
and theologies that say that the body is no longer the person or that the body is worthless
or in play, in this case, the body is the prison house of the soul.
Yeah, right it's when you get
developed ideas like that that bodies start being disposed of but that's not the
instinctual human practice that we see from the very beginning even before
history was being recorded. Yeah I mean it's interesting to know right like for
instance the age you're talking about right that's that's you know kind of the
development of Plato brain period right but if you look at like the like among
the Greeks. If you look at the
stories that they're all still telling, you know, read the Iliad, read the Odyssey, what
exactly happens to a person's body has a huge impact on their experience of, you know,
pagan Greek afterlife, right?
Has a huge, huge impact.
Like, whether the person is buried or not is a big question in those stories.
So they still retain that idea and their least telling stories that have that
in it even as they're starting to develop some of these dualistic approaches to the body.
Yeah, so for folks who don't know since I use the term axial agent I don't know if I've
referred to it before on the show. That's used to refer to the period of time in the mid-first
millennium BC when you get Buddhism first showing up in the east, you get Platonic philosophy showing
up in Greece.
uh... you get well
greek philosophy showing up in gray starting with the priest cradix
uh... you have the classical hebrough profits
in the middle east
uh... so that's uses away of generalizing
about that period of
religious and philosophical self-awareness
in the first millennium bc which we don't have rickett written records of
before that
uh...
That's not just...
say all those phenomena are the same or even related, right?
It's just that at that time in history, probably based on the progress of
technology, writing, et cetera, various cultures reach a higher point of
self-reflection.
Yeah.
They're not doing, not just doing things.
They're talking about and writing about and philosophizing about the stuff
that they do.
Right.
Because when humans are hunting...
gathering, but that doesn't leave a lot of time to think about, you know, what does it all mean?
And same thing with, you know, subsistence farming to try to keep your family alive. You have to
reach a certain level of social advancement, and then you can have people start to think, you know,
what is the correct way to structure a society? Why is our structure the way it is, right? etc, etc.
Why do these things happen? You know, we offered sacrifices to the gods, and these bad things
still happened to why, right?
All those kinds of thoughts require a certain level of societal development.
And several cultures reach that level of development in different parts of the world,
in the middle of the First Millennium BC.
So that's what I was talking about when I say previous to that,
that would we see perials and religious phenomena,
those tend to be religious phenomena that are...
sort of instinctual and built into humanity at some level.
Yeah.
Right.
So sacrificial ritual, everyone does all over the world in similar ways, right?
Before that, the offering of incense, bearing the dead.
There are these sort of severant, they're sort of, therefore we can say are kind of built in some sense into what it is to be human.
Once you get to that period
where that reflection starts to happen, you start getting diverging sort of philosophical
viewpoints about these things because now it's not just a question of what's instinctual
to humanity and how humanity is built, but people can build and create things and create
ideologies for various reasons, et cetera, et cetera.
So what is...
What does it mean or what follows from
Saying that okay
Your identity is not related to your soul
Your identity is related to your body
Right that yourself is a physical self a
Physical self that exists in the world
Right
This has some
drastic effects and how we have to rethink a whole bunch of things.
Yeah, although, I was gonna say it's interesting, right? As I'm pondering this again,
like the fact that I'm a body in the world is actually self-evident. It requires a whole
stack of thinking that that's not true in order for me to
to conceive of myself in some other way.
But we've been fed that.
stack. Yeah. Again, he hit me. Yeah. Right. Yeah. Yeah. Right. But we've been taught, right?
This oh no, the inner me, you know, who I am inside that no one knows. We've all been taught to be
be moracy and it's weird.
And speaking of moracy, as we were,
What part of what this means is that our identity, right, who we are, right?
If ourself is related to our body, who I am is external to me, not internal.
It's not some internal set of internal processes.
Right.
I have this person who I am deep down inside who's longing to get out, but no, I'm trapped.
Right? That's not really.
I am yeah with with and we don't need to go there but we'll just say with massive
implications for a lot of the big debates of our time. Yes right yeah that's not
right but it's who I am it's the body that I am in the world right that's who I
am that means external to me external so there is a process that all humans go
through in adolescence right for some of us it never ends but
That process and this is a very modern process because adolescence is a very modern concept
Right for most of human history and in much of the world today
13 years old as an adult
And that's when you get married often in arranged marriage and start having kids
At your adult now, so there is no adolescence but our modern
modern cultures of the West have
created this thing adolescence, this period where humans are sexually mature, but are not
considered adult by society.
This sort of five year holding pattern, four or five year holding pattern.
And we wonder why there's all these problems, at least.
At least four or five years, yes.
And having created that, right?
Because people aren't sort of let out into the world to become adults as bodies as people in the world.
They're not allowed to sort of become themselves.
They tend to spend a lot of time trying to figure out who they are.
And what they quickly realize is that especially when they were small children,
who they were was an extension of their parents.
parents, their family in general, right?
And so they try to define who they are as an individual over against their parents, over
against their family, over against whatever religious tradition they were brought up in,
over against, over against, over against, right?
And so they sort of push back on all of those things.
So they say, I'm not that and not that and not that and not that.
And so you strip all those things away, strip away all those relationships, familial relationships, social relationships, cultural relationships, community relationships, rip all those away. What do you have left?
Nothing.
You have nothing left.
You don't find some inner soul that has an identity inside of you. You find a big hole.
Right, you find nothing.
And that's why adolescents who go down this road end up being nihilists for at least a
couple of years.
Right.
Well, I think it's also like, you know, maybe to a lesser extent, although sometimes to
a great extent, you know, during during the height of the pandemic when a lot of relationships
were significantly strained or reduced, big uptick in mental health issues and suicide, you
because what it is that the f***.
fine to we are was muted. Right. Right. All these things
are taking away. There's no there's no identity there. Because
so that's sort of the negative way of seeing it. But the positive
way of seeing it is that my identity is a whole series of nested
stacked up relationships. Right. My relationships to my family,
members, my relationships to my community and the different community.
communities that I'm a part of, the my relationships with various movements and thoughts and things
that are going on in society, which we've defined as spirits.
We've done an episode on what spirits are.
You can look at that, right?
The sort of spirits that move me and that I participate in for good or for evil, right?
That of course my relationship with God.
And these relationships all taken together, right?
You stack them all up, each one of those pieces.
And what you get at the end of the stack,
when you look at the whole stack, that's my identity.
That's who Father Stephen D. Young is.
Right?
If you want a real picture of who Father Stephen D. Young
is, you have to have all the pieces.
The more pieces you have, the more full of a picture you have.
Right?
I'm the pastor of a parish.
orthodox priest. I've got a PhD in a particular subject and I did my research on a particular
topic. I'm working on another one. All of these things, right? Here's where I stand
on various issues, right? Here are the things I'm involved in. Here are the hobbies I have.
Here are the things I enjoy. You know, I'm a husband to my wife, right? I'm an uncle to
my nephew. It's on and on and on and on and on and on and on and on and on and on and on.
Right? The more those you pile up, the more those you're aware of, the more complete a picture
you have a few-
I am. Right. And again, our culture has taught us, right, to look at that whole pile of
things and say, okay, but there's this but. Yeah, I must be some kind of unique, special
creature that is not definable by any of those quote unquote labels. Yes. I am a beautiful
You
unique snowflake. The hole is greater than the sum of its parts. That's the positive way.
I won't do the, you know, we're all mulching in the same compost heap joke. But
But with that butt is fake.
It's false.
Right.
trying to rattle and shake your sense of identity. You may wonder why would our culture do that?
What is it about our culture that would try to make it so that you are insecure in your identity?
That's to give us something else. There are a number of reasons. One of them is to sell you things.
Yes.
Yes. Right. I did it. He is now something you express. Yeah.
By how you dress, you have to buy things to wear. You know, and what kind of car you drive,
and what kind of, uh, how you present yourself. Right. Which accounts you follow on Twitter.
Yes. You're supposed to not see yourself as this interlocking web that's, that's a given,
That's an objective thing, right?
And find fulfillment and purpose in all...
those relationships and all of those roles, no, you're supposed to craft an identity for yourself.
Yeah. Which is expensive and exhausting. Yes, because no matter how much of it you do,
you're always aware that you're cosplaying and it's not real.
Right? It's not real. And if it goes far enough, you can ruin all the relationships
that would have given you identity.
in meaning that would have given you a sense of who you are because you've been chasing
after these other superficial things but someone else has been making money off of you while
that's been happening. Someone else has been exploiting you, right? People don't won't just do this
to you to sell you things either, right? People will do this to exploit you sexually, especially young
people be
people will do that, but they're always exploiting you. They're always trying to cast doubt on your
confidence in who you are and what your purpose is and where you should drive meaning in your
life because they want to take something from you. Not because they want to give you a renewed
sense of purpose. And that's why the Matrix worked as a concept for a movie. Yes.
Yeah, right.
So the flip side of that is, right, when we when we re-imbed ourselves in those relationships and in that identity and we accept it, we embrace it and we accept it and embrace the purpose and the meaning that that gives us, we become increasingly impervious to that kind of stuff.
Right.
We don't get suckered in by that kind of thing.
Yeah, people who have healthy in-person relationships.
are much less likely to feel lost and stressed out by everything that's going on in quote-unquote
the world.
So another piece, another important piece here in our first half is that another piece
of this external identity is our actions because our actions are external to us.
We act in the world.
And so our actions in the world are part of what define who we are.
They're part and parcel of those relationships, really, honestly.
Our actual relationship to God is not made up of feelings we might have about God or feelings
that we interpret is...
being from God at various points in our life. Right? The Scriptures are very clear. Our
relationship with God is constituted, is made up of our actions.
Is that works righteousness again, Father Stephen?
Yes. Sorry.
I mean, I need to tally at some point, just so I have the number on hand of how many times
the Scriptures associates loving God with keeping His commandments.
But even if there weren't a bunch...
times which there totally is. Jesus says, if you love me, you will keep my commandments.
Right. I mean, that you can't get clearer than that. Yeah. You can't tell me there's
some other passage of scripture that's clearer than that that you're going to use to reinterpret
that one. Right. That dog don't hunt. Right. If you love Christ, you keep His commandments.
Keeping his commandments is what love is.
Yeah.
right? My love for my wife is not a feeling I have sometimes. Yeah, I mean, I think about this,
you know, John 316, right? Probably the best-known Bible verse, at least in the English speaking
world, I think is misunderstood a lot where it begins for God so loved the world that he gave
was only we got in the sun. The the so there in English is not like...
He loved us so much. Right. It's not an emphatic. It's and I looked this up just to make sure
I was right about this. I can't remember the exact word it is in Greek, but the Greek it's it means in
this manner. For God in this man. Yeah. Love the world that he gave his only begun son. You know,
that that even when the love of God is being described by the scriptures, it's by what God does.
Yes, love is an action of God. Yes, my love for my wife.
his actions. Okay. My love for my wife is not a feeling I have. Right. It's not warm
fuzzies. Right. Those things are nice. If you've got feelings, enjoy them.
Like Boston said, it's more than a feeling. But, but me loving my wife is when I get up
before her, I do a bunch of the things I know she's going to want me to do without her
having to ask me to do them.
That make her life easier
That is loving my wife and has nothing to do with feelings has nothing to do with words
Right, it's what I do
That's you know
There are other very clear passages of the New Testament the person who says he loves God and hates his
Brother is a liar
Yeah, you don't get clearer than that
This is the whole concept of
hypocrisy which is all through the prophets and all through Christ's
criticism of the Pharisees. Right? What you say is great but what you do isn't and
what you do is what's real. Right? What you would write down if I gave you a test
as the right answer is not important. What you say is not important. What you claim
you think, or believe me.
is not important. What you do is important because what you do reflects what you
actually believe and actually think. An actually value, right, and actually think is important.
That is going to naturally express itself in actions which again all through the
New Testament. This is why our actions, our works, are always described as fruit.
Fruit.
Fruit of a tree.
A bad tree can't bring...
fourth good fruit and a good tree won't bring forth bad fruit. The fruit reveals what's inside of us.
Because of that, totally clear in Scripture, no way around it.
And so our actions are right, our identity. So back to Father Andrew's rhetorical questions.
Why am I answering them if I keep calling the rhetorical question?
Why?
I ask you.
That's also a rhetorical question.
Don't answer that either.
But right, talking about our atoms, okay?
Because this is important.
This is key here to understand where we're talking about bodily resurrection.
Because it's not only a question of, you know, yeah, when I die, my body's going to
compose and the atoms and molecules of my body will end up being other things,
right? Like boats and trees and later on other people probably, right? It's not just that,
but even during my life every seven years, all the matter sort of filters out, right?
So when we say that the bodily resurrection my body is going to be restored.
put back together and have life breathed back into it. We're not saying God's
going to take all find all of those atoms and molecules because some of those
will have also been part of other people. Yeah and like you know if you were to
gather up all the atoms I've ever had. Let's just say I would have to go to the
gym a lot more. Who gets custody of which atoms? Right? Right? So that
That's not what we're talking about.
Yeah, yeah.
And that's why the church has always understood
and Judaism, the segments of Judaism,
like Pharisees, that believe in the bodily resurrection
before Christianity, have always understood
that your body gets burned up in a fire,
your body sinks into the bottom of the ocean,
your body gets eaten by an animal
that doesn't stop God from being able to raise you
from the dead, right?
because we're not talking about that.
atoms. Right? We're not talking about the atoms. But what we are talking about is the
externalities that we've been talking about. These have to be restored at the resurrection.
This system of relationships has to be restored at the resurrection. Our works and the person
that is
made us has to be restored at the resurrection. Why? Well because if it's not,
then it's not going to be me who's raised from the dead.
Because my identity is those things.
So some pile of atoms being put together and a human soul breathe,
it, bring breathe into it.
Isn't going to be me.
isn't going to be Father Stephen DeYoung alive again unless these other things are restored,
that form my identity.
Right. And that being the case, right, that being the case, if we understand that that has
to be the case for our identity to continue after death and in the resurrection.
Then we understand that it's that that we mean when we talk about the bodily resurrection.
The restoration of those things is what we mean by the bodily resurrection.
And if that's what we mean by the bodily resurrection, we've got to rethink a lot of other things
about the resurrection too.
Right.
in terms of how we've been taught to either taught to the...
think about it or have sort of lazily thought about it.
Yeah, just imagined it.
Yeah.
And so that's what we're going to be talking about
the rest of tonight.
We'll be starting here with this sense of
what a person's identity is, that being external,
that being bodily, that being in the world
in a system of relationships, right?
and constituted by our acts.
what does it mean for that to be restored on the last day?
That the judgment.
All right, well with that provocative question,
we're going to go ahead and take our first break,
and we'll be right back on the Lord of Spirits.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls on the second half
of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-237-237-237-237-237.
3, 4, 6. That's 855 AF radio.
How do you explain the sacraments? It's easy to say they're mysteries that we have to take
on faith or on the authority of tradition, but that is not how the early Christians understood
them. To them, and to all ancient people, the idea that physical objects had spiritual
power was very intuitive. Whereas modern people tend to find this difficult, bizarre, or
or even, un-Christian. This is because we live in an era shaped by secularism, a way of
viewing a world that's incompatible with sacramental thinking. Because secular ideas
are at the heart of our culture, modern people tend to think in secular ways without realizing
it, even the most well-meaning of us. How then do we live in, but not be of, a secular
culture? We need to understand the enchanted, sacramental way that the early Christians
viewed the world, but we also need to understand secularism.
What is it really?
Where did it come from? And how does it influence how we think about religion?
Journey to Reality, Sacramento Life in a secular age, breaks down these important issues
in accessible, non-academic language and is an ideal introduction for young readers,
catechumans and seekers, as well as for any Orthodox Christians who want to deepen their
understanding of the sacraments.
Journey to Reality, Sacramento Life in a Secular Age by Zachary Porcou, now available at
store.EngineFaith.com.
Again.
at isstore.angianfaith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits,
the Father Andrew Stephen Damick,
and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Thanks, boys and Steve.
So, I don't know, do you think people's brains
are sufficiently bent yet or do we need to keep bending
until they...
somebody's napping. We are going to keep bending. People are being warned.
Yeah, I do want to I do want to tell everybody, by the way, just for sake of
reference because you know, by this point, we don't expect everyone to have
listened to every episode, but really you should listen every episode. But if
you really want to know to have a lot more kind of fleshing out fun, fun fully
intended, fun, fully intended, make sure you check out some of our early
episodes on bodies that we...
I think that was like that was in the first year, if I recall correctly, wasn't it?
Yeah, the bodies in the bodyless episode, I think it was yeah, and then one called God's body.
Yeah, and it was still the soul about the soul.
Yeah, yeah, so this one's, this is definitely a hyperlinked episode in a lot of ways, but yeah,
we're kind of taking it from a different angle in this case, right? But if you're interested,
especially those questions of like what about the atoms and all that stuff.
Um, you should oh the, uh, the photo thesis episode too.
Yes, exactly, exactly.
I probably the relics episode.
Oh, yes.
That one's called, uh, can these bones live?
This whole thing's derivative.
Why are we even doing this?
Like, I don't know.
Good night.
Why am I even here?
Yeah.
What does it all mean?
So, yeah.
Yeah, so we're talking about the bodily
resurrection. And we began in the first, the first half of this episode, beginning talking about
identity. And we're going to get even deeper into that now. But the main point of the first
half, everybody was that identity is actually external to the, to the human, because we're part
of a web of relationships and our actions and all that, that kind of stuff. So it's very, we
the body in the world.
Exactly.
exactly. So I take it from that
pre-ebbled we haven't gotten a bunch of calls yet because people are like just
no I know actually you know what it looks like we're there is a call coming in
it looks like I don't know should we have Trudy just line it up just cold and
like just bring it right in let's just bring it right in okay Trudy we're just
gonna go ahead and take Luke do it live Luke your phone says you're from Montana
Are you really calling from Montana?
Yeah.
There's time.
Right.
What are the, my other people in Montana doing right now?
I don't know.
Oh, you're nowhere near them.
That's right.
You are from Montana.
They're eating a stuckey's, obviously.
So look, look,
welcome to the Lotus Pears podcast.
What's on your mind?
Yeah, so it's kind of related to the,
like the phenomenology that you guys have been describing,
like that being is a verb, you know?
And, um,
So I don't I mean I guess it's kind of somewhat related to this, but it's more
You know Jonathan Pajot had this video called there is no literal meaning and like I don't know if you guys have like
Looked into him much better
But like is it Canadian?
He's one of my favorite Kenuka Stanis. Yeah
Not my favorite but like he's up
Yeah.
We have shadow.
as the world's greatest Canadian, as we all know.
Sorry Luke, go ahead.
Yeah, so there's the four senses of scripture.
Right there's the literal.
There's the anagogical, like the moral and the,
to have the other one.
But, so I'm trying to understand,
like, is there a way we can, like,
other senses of the word literal?
Because, like, I'm Roman Catholic and like in our Catholicism,
says you know it describes these four senses.
in that the literal, all other senses are based on the literal, so there's a literal and
a spiritual meaning.
Like, do you think this can be reconciled with this other way in which there is no literal
meaning in the sense that, as Pigeon describes it, that there's no, you can't give a direct
description of something, like dissociated from any perspective, if that makes sense.
You wait.
I don't know that I've watched that video by him, but by the way, we're not just being
KG, we actually do know him.
Yeah.
So, like, the way that we use the word literal now is different from the way that it was
used in many centuries before now, especially talking about the four senses of Scripture.
Right now when we say literal we mean...
I don't know, I think we tend to mean material maybe.
I think that that's kind of what people mean by literally, although in my head, I hear
Rob Lowe saying that on Parks and Rec.
But no, I mean, in its most basic sense, historically, it just means the thing as it is written,
right?
So sort of the kind of the immediate sense of the words on the page is the literal, the
But it doesn't mean materially, necessarily.
So, like, I also heard it described, sorry, the, like, as the word as the author originally intended them.
Well, that's a whole new ball of wax right there.
Yeah.
Yeah. So, yeah, I think from your description, I haven't watched the, the Peugeot video either.
And, you know, he doesn't watch mine, so I don't feel bad.
Um.
But that particular, but it sounds like for what you said, right, that I think you may be
confusing the idea of ideas of literal and objective.
So like I would agree with the statement, right, we've said before on the show, right, that Thomas Nagel quote, there is no view from nowhere.
Right, so every statement I make comes from my perspective, right?
So yeah, there is no real objectivity. There's
only subjectivity. But I don't think that's the same thing as talking about the literal
meaning of a text. Right. I think what's meant by census literalis is that you begin with
right. See this the place where people run into troubles are always jumping to historical
text but let's use a text we've already referred to tonight right.
Christ says if you love me.
you will keep my commandments. So the literal sense of that is kind of obvious to
us. If I love Jesus and I want to show that I love Jesus I should do that by
keeping his commandments by doing the things that he told me to do. That's not
objective in the sense that that's clearly there's a whole frame in which those
ideas exist.
the concept of commandments, the concepts of who Jesus is, right? And all these other things.
And you can't just generalize from that, right? That isn't what it means to love everyone,
right? Loving my wife doesn't mean keeping her commandments. She may disagree.
Let's get her on the line. Where's Trins? Oh man, we need to have her call in some day. I'm just saying
That's not like some kind of objective definition of love or something, right?
That's very subjective and contextual. It talks about our relationship with Jesus.
We have to understand who Jesus is to really understand what that means, etc., etc.
But there's still a literal meaning there of, yes, I love Jesus.
I want to express what I love for him. So I'm going to do the things that he
But there's still a literal meaning there of yes, I love Jesus. I want to express why I love for him. So I'm going to do the things that he
that he said I should do.
Right?
But that also doesn't have to be the end of discussion, right?
And that's what the other meanings are about, right?
And the reason why those other meanings are grounded
in the literal sense is you don't sort of dump the literal sense.
So we don't keep talking about that passage
and other things that it means and say,
so forget about keeping Jesus command,
but you don't have to worry about that, actually.
Yes.
of them metaphor. Right. Right. That's not what we're saying. We say no, that is true. But then we
could also go further than that. Right. We could go deeper into it. Right. And say sort of like we
were doing tonight, we could take that into a broader sense and say, Oh, look, love isn't a feeling.
love consists of actions. Right? That's not literally what Jesus is
saying, Jesus is not trying to communicate as a general principle, love consists of actions.
Right. He's saying something more specific than that. But that is something we can reasonably
conclude from it. Right. Oh, there's the literal meaning, the sort of direct meaning. What is being
said to us? And then we can add to that deeper meanings, connections to other parts of scripture,
all of those kind of things. Yeah. Does that make sense, Luke?
I think so. So just to like repeat what you said a little bit me. Yeah. So it's kind of like literal is like.
It's like relative to those other senses. It's kind of lower down and it's something that can be kind of applied.
Is it? If that makes sense? Like I would say that I would say I would say that those other senses are relative to the literal.
You know, because that's the sort of the first place that you go is the literal.
Like what's the thing that is being said here, you know, it's straightforward.
Let me give it another example, maybe this will help.
So this is from this will tell you the whole Council of God Bible study is actually far in advance
of what's being released currently.
But so last night in real time, we were talking about the construction of the table of the show bread
In the tab.
So the literal sense is that God shows and tells Moses to make an actual table on which there was going to be actual bread so that the priests who were serving in the tabernacle would have bread to eat during their time of service.
Right, so that's like the literal sense of what's being said there.
Right, it's describing this actual table, this actual piece of furniture that was part
of the tabernacle, how it was transported and care.
it's construction. That's the literal sense of the text, right? But you can go
from there too, and then we've talked about this on the show way back when we
talked about the tabernacle, that in most pagan temples at that time you would
have tables, but those tables were where where food was brought to feed to the
God, to feed to the idol. And so this table, God's table in the tabernacle is sort
an inversion.
of that, right, that God is feeding his priests. Preces aren't coming and feeding God. Right?
Now, the text in Exodus doesn't make that point that I just made. Doesn't say anything about
pagan temples. Doesn't make that comparison. Right? So that's another level of meaning
by taking what is an Exodus and taking it in context.
And another thing I can point out is I can compare that to at least in our Orthodox churches
and in Eastern right Roman Catholic churches, you've got a prosthesis table, right, usually
in the in the altar area where you have the bread that's going to be used in the Eucharist,
right?
And I can make that connection to our current usage and talk about the Eucharist and talk
about God feeding us, right?
So.
So those other two points I just made, I think are valid points, and I think they're valid
points to make from the text in Exodus, but they aren't sort of explicitly literally
there in Exodus.
Right?
But we have to start with what's literally there, this table that existed in the tabernacle.
And we understand that, and then once we understand that, we can make these other theological
connections and see this greater significance.
Yeah, so I think so. So like the literal sense is kind of like a launching ground. It's
almost like maybe like it can't just exist by itself, but it can, it's a, it's like a
launching point for other, other levels of interpretation sort of.
Yeah, I mean, if it was just the literal sense, it would be in irrelevant detail.
Yeah, in many cases.
But I mean, but like, like, you know, I'll give an example.
Like if I tell one of my kids, okay, go to your room.
Okay, the literal thing that needs to happen is the kid needs to relocate himself and go into the room.
Now, he may along the way ask himself, now why did he send me to my room?
Right? That would be another sense.
Right?
Yeah.
asking what does this mean?
You know, how can I avoid this in the future?
You know, that sort of thing.
Um, so yeah.
Yeah.
Okay, yeah, I think that'll make...
We just focus too much on the little sense and we think that it's sort of an end in itself.
Right. Right. But if you get rid of the literal sense, right, then the other things you can go into all kinds of wild speculation that has that, you know, go all kinds of weird places.
Yeah. So you don't get rid of the literal sense because that kind of grounds you.
Right. We're still talking about God's table.
We're still talking about bread.
right? Yeah, it has to be it's connected to something, right? It's not just
whatever wild speculations I want to. Not just images or whatever. So yeah.
All right. Well, Luke, thank you very much for calling nice to speak with you.
All right. We're going to go ahead and take another caller. We have Charles who has
a question about the bodily resurrection. Charles, welcome to the Lord's Spirit's podcast.
God bless you.
So are you a Charlie guy or a
Chuck Guy or neither.
Chaz.
Oh, neither father.
I'm definitely a full-out Charles.
OK.
All right.
We'll stick with that then.
So Charles, what's your thought?
So in the first half, talking about the resurrection
not being just restoring the atoms that were once there,
that part I'm totally following on.
But I like my question.
I guess how I'm trying to ask Father is dormitian and our blessed lady, like they, you know,
she, her body is assumed. Like, and I understand that like Lazarus wasn't resurrected in the same way.
Lazarus was more like resuscitated. He's still a parents death after. So I'm trying to like put
my mind together on how you know it's only a few
say, you know, like Enoch or Elijah or or blessed lady, like how does that work? Or is that
I'm just overstretching my mind? I just need focus on me. Yeah, yeah. So so a couple of things.
Number one, she did die, right? You know, the orthodox church is very explicit about the fact that
she died. Now, Enoch, you know, it just says he was taken up. Same thing with with the prophet Elijah.
But you know, St. Paul, when he talks about the relationship of the body in the resurrection to the relationship to the body as it is in this life, he uses the analogy of a plant to a seed.
Right.
So the seed is this life.
You know, so the human body is going to be significantly altered.
And it's not just about the atoms.
Ultimately, the atoms don't matter that much.
Pun intended, I guess.
Because as we mentioned, you trade out your atoms all the time.
Right, there's atoms you're no longer using
that you were using last week.
So it's not about that particular set of atoms,
but the human body is going to be transformed
in a way that is hard for us to understand,
but this is part of what it means that when Christ,
I'm gonna talk about this.
this at the end a little bit more, but when Christ says we will be equal to the angels in the
resurrection, it doesn't mean that we become angel kind, right? But we will function more like they do.
So there is going to be a change in the human body. The human body will take on other kinds of
abilities and characteristics. We will no longer have the mortality that we now have. We will still be
material, but exactly what the character of that materiality will be.
We don't really understand, or even, I would say,
even partly understand now, just a little glimpse maybe.
So yeah, there is gonna be this elevation and exaltation
to the human body that's gonna happen in the resurrection.
And so we see that already with the saints.
So even though some, there's no remains,
a handful of them, right?
So the phytotocos, as you mentioned,
is definitely one of those.
The basic state of the scenes in the life of the age to come is essentially the same.
They're all participating in the resurrection in one way or another.
Some it seems more than others, but what does it mean for them?
Is it going to be different for what it means to us from our vantage point?
Like, we're still experiencing it in terms of time, which is why this is actually a sequel to the previous episode,
where we talked about time.
you know, it would be reasonable to say I think that they're experiencing the
resurrection now, even though from our point of view, most of them have not been resurrected,
right?
Okay.
But they are functioning in that angelic way.
Again, they're not.
They don't turn into angels, but they become equal to the angels.
I mean, that's what Jesus says.
Does that make sense?
Yes, it does Father.
Thank you very much.
Yeah, yeah.
I don't know, Father Stevens, do you want to attract, multiply, divide anything?
Let me use this opportunity to condition something in terms of our discussion tonight.
So hmm.
We're not going to give you like, okay, here's how the bodily resurrection works.
It's some kind of literal sense, right?
Because the scriptures don't do that because they can't. This isn't something we can fully understand.
What the scriptures give us when they talk about what happens to us after the end of our life in this world.
Well, the Scriptures give us is a whole bunch of metaphors and illusions.
and images that give us sort of ways of thinking about it.
And so what we're aiming to do tonight
and talking about the bodily resurrection
is to give a way of thinking about it.
That I think ultimately, this is where we're going to end up,
spoilers at the end of the third half,
is talking about why what we're sort of constructing here
as a way of thinking about it
helps us understand a lot of things.
that the scriptures say, a lot of things that the fathers say, a lot of things that Orthodox
theologians and spiritual fathers and things say, that seem kind of weird and maybe unintelligible
because of the way we're used to thinking about these things.
But if we look at it from a little different perspective, some of those things they say
start to click and make a little more sense.
but still they make sense at that level of imagery and illusion and
way of thinking about it, not at the level of, okay, now I get it, this is exactly how it's
going to be. So that's at the core of what we're getting at when we talk about the Theotocos
or Moses or Elijah or Enek, or frankly any of the saints is that they have already experienced
the bodily resurrection that we're talking about from their perspective.
Yeah, right and this gets into some time you whine me stuff
But St. Paul is the one who drops on us in Ephesians that were already seated with Christ in the heavenly places
So it's not our fault
You all right, we learned it by watching you. That's that's right. So thank you very much for calling Charles
I hope that's helpful
It was it was thank you Paul. Cool. All right. We're gonna continue on
on.
here with the second half. So identity end. Since you just mentioned time, was that a deliberate
segue there, father? Yeah.
Wiggly, Wiggly, Timmy, whimy stuff. We're going to say it is now. Yeah.
Uh, the red dot. Can't prove it wasn't. Um, so yeah, so we have to not only in the first
half, we're talking about identity as being external, but you know, just internal versus external,
All right, these are spatial terms we're using.
Yeah.
Right.
and that our life is in, we're a body in the world, right?
We're talking in spatial terms, relational terms
with other people and things in the world.
We also have to put this into the context of time.
And here's why, because this is another aspect
of our identity, right?
We concluded the first half by saying
the goal of the doctrine of the bodily resurrection
Is that?
But this is the way to talk about the fact that my identity, your identity, is going to
survive our physical death in this world.
That not just any person is going to live again, but Father Steven Diug, Father Andrew
Damak Charles who just called in is going to live again.
And B.
that person have that same identity. And so that means you have to take time into account because
the externalities we were talking about in the first half related to identity, those relationships,
for example, those change over time over the course of our lives. Right? So a young boy becomes a
a single man becomes a husband, becomes a widower.
Each of those things is a key part of that person's identity in each of those phases of his life.
But they're not all true of him at the same time.
Yeah, right. A young girl becomes an adult woman becomes an old one, right? Those
relationships are
relationships change over time, right in shift. And so our identity is not just something external to us in
relationship to other people and things in the world in spatial terms, but our identity is stretched out or spread out through the time of our
earthly life.
Yeah, and this world. I mean, even just thinking about like like listeners think about your own life, right? So
So if you got a decent number of years behind you, you can
remember things that you did when you were younger that you now you're like I can't believe I did that right well the
reason that you did it is at the time it seemed like a good idea. Now you wouldn't say well that wasn't me it was you right but it's it's also not
who you are now but you're not something someone other than that that younger version of yourself right so it's both what you did
then and what you think about it.
Now are part of your identity, right?
So there's a temporal facet to who it is that you are.
Right, right.
And, you know, we've all had relationships begin and end.
Yeah, right.
Like, first 34 years of my life, well not first 34 years,
from age 13 to age 34.
That's over
20 years of my life, I had a best friend. Right. He was the best man at my wedding. I was the best man at his wedding.
Right. I don't know what it's like to be him or a bat. But for me, right. His friendship was part of my identity. Right.
We've fallen out of contact. I haven't been in contact with him for 10 years. Right. So that relationship isn't
constitutive of my identity anymore.
The way it was, if you go back 15 years or 20 years.
Yeah, and we've all experienced
behaving in a certain way with certain people.
And then not anymore, you know.
Yeah, being the husband of my wife
is a core part of my identity now.
There was a couple of decades where I didn't know her.
And therefore it wasn't Lord willing and odds are all diverse so I won't have to experience
the other end of that.
But so this is just a reality, right?
Who you are, right?
These things don't usually, very rarely, right?
God blesses us with a long life in this world.
Right.
the average of life span now is 74.
So if you live in the United States at least,
if you live 74 years, right,
your parents are probably not gonna be alive
that whole 74 years.
Not impossible, but odds are good, right,
but they're not gonna be.
And obviously, if you have children,
they're not gonna be alive for the first part of that, right?
Right, so all of these things are true.
But what that means is...
Our identity who I am, who you are, is not a snapshot.
It's not a snapshot of any particular action you take or any relationship you have,
that we talked about in the first half, but it's also not a snapshot of any particular moment in your life.
life, right? And that is who you are and what happens after or who you are after or who
you were before.
doesn't matter. Right, sort of that snapshot is just it. Right, like that's it. So when
we're saying that your identity is sort of spread out across the whole span of your life
in this world, that means your identities is certain since the sum total of all of that.
The same way it's the sum total of all your relationships stacked up with some total
of your actions, it's the sum total of all of those
use right across across your entire life right and that that snapshot right we
tend to we tend to hold that a person sort of is one particular version of
right. Sometimes that's because someone has died and there's a version
of them that we want to remember. Yeah. Maybe as opposed to other ones. Yeah.
We want to sort of deny certain parts or we want to polish up certain parts. But
your identity is not who you are the last second that you're alive. Right. Right.
Right, especially, right, like people who may suffer dementia at the end of their life.
Right.
Yeah, and I mean, you know, the family members that experience that with them will often say
things like he's not himself. Yeah. Right. You know, he is that person in front of them,
that forgetful person in front of them, but he's also what they remember about him.
That doesn't go away. And you know, even like not just temporarily, but you know, between
multiple relationships. Like, for instance, we've all had the experience of having something
being said about someone that we know well.
being kind of shocked, like, wait a minute, that's not the Bob I know. Right. But then
maybe you find out that that is him also. That is Bob. Yeah. Bob, the one you know, Bob
functions this way in this relationship and this way in another relationship and this way
in your relationship with him. You know, that and that's that's the reality of each of us,
right? Like, you're a different person with different people and you're a different person
with multiple people at the same time, depending on which group it is.
Yeah, and even if you maintain your complete mental acuity up to the last moment of your life, right?
We've criticized before many times, right?
many many times
The the whole 19th century German
You know all of history has led up to this moment, right?
We now stand at the pinnacle, right?
But that's no more true when it's applied to your own life.
that it is when it's applied to history in general.
Yeah.
Because we don't all just make continual progress our whole life.
I know.
Imagine when I'm first waking up in the morning before coffee
and then applying that thought,
all of my life has led up to this moment
in the way that I feel right now.
Please know.
Yeah, yeah.
But even in the sense that sometimes we regress.
Oh, sure.
Yeah.
Right.
Not me, man.
Orally, maybe.
Orally, spiritually.
Right.
We have ups and downs, not just ups.
Not just sort of a, you know,
the ladder of divine is set.
It's a great image for what it's an image of.
Right.
But you should not take from that.
That the Christian life is just going up one wrong after another.
Right?
Like, your whole life, that's, if you've actually read the book, you know, that's not what
it's about, right?
But who actually reads books anymore?
Come on.
Right?
So it's not just, and the reason why this is very important, right?
The reason why this is very important is, and we're going to, as we keep going in this
this half we're going to get to this in terms of
the judgment. But we tend to have this view and there are certain theological constructs,
like the idea within Roman Catholicism of a state of grace that led themselves to this unfortunately,
to this kind of thinking, unfortunately. Where we think that like if we happen to die at the wrong time,
That's going to make some kind of huge difference in what happens after this life.
Yeah, which there are a whole theology is built on that idea.
Yes.
There are.
Just look up the phrase state of grace.
Yes, exactly.
And you will see, right?
And it leads itself to that, right?
That, you know, Hamlet doesn't want to kill.
It is.
It is what it kills.
I go because, right, he's praying.
Yeah
I don't know if I can kill him, Lee's prey.
Yeah, because he doesn't want to send him to heaven.
Yes.
So I'm going to wait until I catch him sinning and then I'll kill him.
So he goes to hell, right?
Yeah.
That's not how this works.
It's not how this works.
Okay.
I mean, I'm sorry.
I don't think most Roman Catholics take the kind of legalistic interpretation that can be
taken of some of their doctrine in this regard.
Right.
like. So when it was otherwise a saint skips a mass once a
niggas, it's hit by a bus and goes to hell. Right. I don't
think most Catholics actually believe that. I don't think
so. That kind of legalistic interpretation. But bits of
that work and do our thinking. Right. And that includes when
we think about other people. Right. That includes when we
think about other people. So the person who Christ is going to
Bye bye.
on the last day is the whole person. Not the person at their last moment if that last
moment was a dark moment or a moment of weakness. It's the whole person, right? Not their worst
moment, not just their best moment, no snapshot. It's the whole person and that whole person
is that whole identity is spread out over to the time of their whole life.
Yeah.
And I mean, I...
I think for instance, about, I mean, to me, this is one of the classic examples, the life
of St. Mary of Egypt.
Right?
I mean, if you talked about only the bit at the end, then yeah, that would lend you to think,
okay, yes, wow, what a saint, right?
And absolutely, absolutely, amazing, amazing saint.
But the bit at the end.
is part of a much larger arc, which includes all the bits at the beginning too.
Right? But they hang together as this single story. And that is who St. Mary of Egypt is.
Right? It's not only this incredible desert dwelling aesthetic. It's also the, you know,
the profligate young woman who's just obsessed with lust.
And it's not like God is going to say, oh.
well, you know, you spent so many years doing this, so many years doing this.
So let me work out the balance here.
That's not, that's not what that means.
It's rather that, that all together it creates this single arc, you know, so that the
arc of a human person is, as you said, more than just a snapshot, more than the bit at
the end.
And in her case, the stuff at the end is made much more powerful and meaningful for us
anyway by all the precedes it, frankly.
You know, that's why it's an incredible story.
Right, and that isn't erased. Right. Isn't edited out. Right. This is an important part of right right away in the Hebrew Scriptures. Right. The Hebrew Scriptures do not shy away from showing even the people who are elevated as great iconic saints in the Hebrew Scriptures, like David, like Abraham, right, like Moses. Yeah.
Get rid of the
Christians have no qualms about talking about places where they send.
Yeah, it did wrong and fell short, right?
Talking about Moses having God so angry at him he's ready to kill him.
Right, because his disobedience, right?
Like this is the kind of thing that gets edited out of pagan stories about heroes.
Absolutely, because weakness is worthlessness within the pagan context.
you
But this is part of the story.
This is part of the story because this is part of who,
part of who David is, is the man who repents.
Right, who sins mightily and repents even more mightily.
Yeah.
Right.
I mean, is that what the Lord says about the one's informant?
You know, it was the one who's forgiven much loves much.
Yeah.
And so, right, it's the, it's the whole, so identity, the identity of a person, my identity,
your identity, the identity of the saints we've been talking about, right? Anyone's identity is
A life. A life. This is why we read the lives of the saints.
Right, we don't just read a list. Right, we have lists.
Right, so it's always a martyr but no, it's their life. When did they live? Where?
What are these events that happened? Right? That's who they are. We instinctively know this. That's why people buy biographies.
Hmm, yeah, I don't know.
Right? Like, who cares about Grover Cleveland's elementary school education?
What does that have to do with any of that?
You just...
made someone's PhD dissertation not matter.
Come on.
Well, no, but my point is people want to read that.
People are drawn to that and want to read that.
They want to know because part of knowing who this person is is
knowing where they came from.
Yeah.
What relationships they had and what experiences they had and what
they did and how they responded to that, right?
That's who they are.
Oh, right.
Not just the things Grover Cleveland did as president.
Right? It is two non consecutive terms.
The it's what?
It's his whole life, right? That's why people want to read biographies.
A whole life is right it. So,
your identity, if you're alive, right?
If you're alive right now and listening to this if you're dead right now
listening to this, I have less to say to you. I don't know what it's like. We'd like to hear
from you. Yes, but call in. Please call in.
Art Bell now. We are officially on to our culture. Right. But if you're alive right now,
right, then your identity is something that's still being formed.
Yep, yep, right, and this is what is
so key in terms of the concept of repentance in the Christian life, right? Is that you may look
back at all the selves you've been over the course of your life with disgust, right? And you may even
be right to do so. Other people, if they knew everything might share your disgust, but that doesn't
mean that's who you need to be tomorrow or the next day or the day after that or the rest of your life,
and whoever you become.
Now, with however much time you have left in your life in this world, is going to shape,
is going to conclude, is going to fill out that story and who you are.
Right? That's still being formed. That's not something, right, who you are is not something
that sorry Calvinists God decreed at some time in the past. And now it's just sort of playing out
you're watching it happen. It's not something you have to dig around and discover. Something that's
being formed in time and space.
You relate to people and you live and you act in the world.
You do things because A life, right?
A life, which is your identity, is what you're living in and through your body.
You can't live A life abstracted from your body.
That's why the internet isn't real.
So, I Twitter isn't real.
That's why Facebook is it real?
That's not living.
And a life has lived.
We talked last time about a world and age.
Right.
It's meaning it's related to other people in the world and other things in the world.
Right. It's fully embedded.
Yeah. And across a particular span of time.
If you live the average life expectancy of 74 years...
It's a particular 74 years in the world
Going from one date to another date, right
Your life is lived with other people
right and as we've talked about the show before
right if if we take you and
We pluck you out of your world
Right your phenomenological world the world of your experience. We pluck you out of your time
We pluck you out of all your relations.
relationships, we pluck you out of your body, right?
You have no identity.
There's nothing left.
Right?
This is why as we've said before on the show,
we like sometimes to sit around and imagine,
what would it have been like if I had been born in 13th century France?
Right?
But that's not an intelligible sentence because if quote unquote, I was born in
And...
13th century France, it wouldn't be me.
Yeah, your accent would be very different.
Yes, I'd be shorter.
Yes.
I'd have a different hair color.
But, right, but not just those that, yes, I would have a different body.
It's rather headed the way out, right?
But I would be surrounded by different people and have different kinds of relationships
with different people.
I would live across a different span of years in a-
different culture with a different religious practice, with a different community.
There is a different set of opinions about the English.
There's literally nothing about me that would be the same, so it wouldn't be me.
Yeah. Right. You couldn't say it would be me. Right.
Because I am in the sense of identity, all of those things.
Right? All of those things. And what this ultimately means, right, is not just, well, it's
fun to think about what it would be like to live in another time, but that's impossible,
right? That's just kind of a bummer. What this really means more importantly is that the
whole idea of individualism that our whole modern society is built upon, sort of the core
principles of modernism is individualism is a lie.
There is no such thing as an individual.
By definition, the individual is nothing.
Yeah, there's persons, and person means relationship.
Right.
Yep, yep.
All right, well believe it or not, you've wasted two perfectly good
halves of your life on the Lord of Spirits podcast.
Well, I hope they have it wasted two halves of their life.
Well see there's just like this video
Rob dead? This so has three halves. A human's life might have more than two halves.
I give it 10,000 halves. You never know.
Right, kill off our audience.
Anyway, right. So we're gonna go ahead and take our second break and we'll be right back.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymeck and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment.
to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
The top 10 reasons to attend the ancient faith men's retreat.
Number one, fellowship with other Orthodox Christian men.
Number two, hearing from four speakers, all priests
and one high-remunk.
Number three, daily matins and vespers
plus an acethyst on Friday and Divine Living.
on Sunday.
4.
Supplication at the Relics of St. Rafael and learning about his life in the Antiochian
Village Museum.
5.
Giving Back to Antiochian Village through a service project.
6.
Enjoying the beautiful grounds of Antiochian Village including the Meditation Trail in
Hikes.
7.
Football During Free Time.
8.
Delicious Breakfast Lunch and Dinner.
9.
on fires and s'mores each night.
And number 10, the opportunity to learn and be encouraged in what it means to be a man.
August 22nd through the 25th, 2024 at Antiochian Village in Bolivar, Pennsylvania.
For more information and to register, just click on the banner on the Ancient Faith website
homepage or the lead graphic on the AFM app.
We really hope to see you there.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Back.
It's a Slorispear's podcast.
And may you have many halves of your life.
Number 11, may you have many halves of your life.
We do have some callers lined up, Father Stephen.
people have curiosity about what
It means to be bodily raised.
Well, hopefully there.
Cats.
Yeah.
The T.S. Eliot set up poems was way better than the musical.
I will die on that hill, everybody.
So I believe the conspiracy theory put forward by the unbreakable Kimmy Schmidt that cats
is not real.
It's not a real musical.
It is a different set of improv done every night by out-of-work actors.
I am on board pretending.
I'm a job.
Yeah.
That includes the movie, too, isn't it?
Yes.
Yeah, which no sane human should ever watch.
So we do have some callers.
First we're going to take Timothy.
So Timothy, welcome to Lord of Spheres podcast.
Hi, how are you all doing?
Good.
How are you?
I'm good.
I'm down here in Georgia.
Yeah, he's a Southern accent.
I'm assuming you don't mean Republic of Georgia.
It's that the...
not that my accent would be a little different
Yeah.
So Timothy, what's on your mind down there in Georgia?
Well, I'm an orthodox convert.
And before I converted, I converted when I got married,
my mother had passed.
And her last wish is were to be cremated.
She didn't want to put a big burden of expense.
She was fully disabled at the end of her life, had no savings.
So she didn't want to pass on the cost of the funeral
to her children.
and so she wanted to...
as a cremator, which we did.
And, Tom becoming orthodox,
I discovered that the orthodox won't,
you know, cremation is not an option after you die.
So my question is, did disinfect hair salvation?
And am I, or any of my brothers,
couple of both, because we went through
with her final wishes.
I know this is probably a pretty dark question,
but it's been plaguing me.
And I really would like to get some feedback on it.
That's a good question.
Um, the short answer is no, right?
Uh, in terms of does it affect her salvation, right?
Um, it's not like, from what you said anyways, it's not like she thought, well,
I'm going to be cremated because I don't believe in the bodily resurrection.
And I want to do everything I can to thwart it.
Right.
I doubt that was her, her deal.
And my guess is that was not the intention of your family either.
You know, you didn't have the context, right?
It's not like from what you said,
anyone started.
Oh, kind of cut it in and out there a little bit.
But yeah, so, so absolutely,
you know, the fact that she was cremated
does not mean that her possibility of salvation is under inquestant.
The reason why the Orthodox Church does not traditionally do funeral
funeral
for those who have been cremated is precisely because number one, it's to emphasize the
resurrection of the body, right? And so if a body is going to be raised and you know that
and you understand that burial is the traditional practice, then you would not do that to a human
being, right? If you have that understanding. So the context in which funerals are refused
for those who have been cremated is the context.
of someone that's deliberately disobeying that, right?
Now, still probably even if someone was like,
I'm trying to think of a context in which someone would,
you know, that would be, it would get done.
And I guess maybe people who are out of touch with the church
and kind of don't know its teachings or whatever,
and then they're dead, and they're cremated,
and then someone calls the priest, I don't know.
You know, but in any event, the point is, as I said,
to underline
the practice of burial as being the norm. Now, if someone, let's say someone dies in a fire,
right? Which is similar in a lot of ways, although it's not quite the same because cremation,
frankly, involves not just the burning of the flesh, but also the crushing of the bones,
right? Because bones don't burn up. You know, so someone who dies in a fire, they're still the
remains of their bones. Would if you know what we've done for them, yeah, sure. You know,
someone who dies on a fire? I mean St. Pauli Carp was
killed with fire. That was his martyrdom and it says explicitly in his life that they collected
his bones as precious relics. So there was no sense of that something shameful had happened
to him as a result of that. So yeah I would say, the thing is, well okay you know better now.
So make sure you put in your will that your burial is to be done according to the
the tritians to Orthodox church.
And since we you brought it up.
I want to say by the way that a lot of people do have this sense that cremation is the cheapest
option.
That is not always true.
And a lot of times people don't know that there are other options that can sometimes
be less expensive.
And let me suggest that a lot more parishes need to do with some parishes have done and
take it upon themselves to help take care of people's bodies.
Like there are a whole, there are a whole parishes where funeral homes are almost never involved
the burial of their people because the people...
the parish take care of that person's body and maybe all you have to do is hire
like a grave digger, you know, to do what's needed in the cemetery, right? And
even then there are some cases where you get a lot of the men of the
parish will get together and dig the grave. So, you know, it's not like we didn't
have burials before someone invented the backhoe, right? So, so that's those
Those things are all possibilities.
Funerales do not need to be...
big expensive things that they often can be now.
But I think because a lot of times we function in,
in frankly, in ignorance, we just don't know
that there are other options.
That's always things.
It's like, well, I want to be the least burden.
So please have me cremated.
And I understand if someone does not know,
but that's part of why I'm saying this now,
there are other options.
So, um,
Yeah, that's totally a thing.
I don't know if father, do you want to add anything
or to any of that?
Well, just on the larger, on the larger issue,
God loves you as he loves your mom
and he's not waiting for you to break a rule
that you don't even know about.
So he can lower the boom on you.
Really?
That's not who God is.
I know we've been...
taught by cultural stuff that that's who God is, that's not who God is. We're going to
go into damnation. We're going to get into this a little bit in the third half, but anybody
who experiences the negative side of the last judgment, if there is anyone, anyone who
does experience that, it's going to be because they chose and pursued that. Not because
they messed up or because...
God relegated them to it.
It's not how God works.
Yeah.
So thank you very much for your answers.
You're welcome.
And, you know, pray for your mother's soul because that's what Orthodox Christians do.
I do do that.
Yeah. Good.
Good. Well, thanks for calling Timothy.
All right. Well, we now have Bethany calling.
So Bethany, welcome to Lord Spirit's podcast.
Hi, I'm also calling for Montana.
the three people in the state.
What?
We've had two thirds of Montana call us tonight.
That's amazing.
Can you see out on the horizon the previous caller?
No, I can't.
OK.
I can see mountains and trees.
Maybe I look closely.
I might see a grizzly bear.
Montana stereotypes confirmed.
Yeah.
Well, Bethany from Montana, what is on your mind this evening?
And my question has to do with interiority and exteriority regarding our faith.
And because you've mentioned, I think Father Andrew you mentioned this when he went on
Dhanis and Zorjo, unlike how martyrdom does not wipe out the stain of heresy.
However, we have Ethiopian martyrs.
And then we've also talked about how, like, you can hear hear...
the coffee hour and how some things did some interesting things but they're
things because of they look holy light and then I read a lot of divine
dissent this lens after reading a late person's guide first and we get to this
one point of let's see if I remember correctly where we have this one
Everyone thought he was a good, nice, good mouth.
But then in his file hours he's like going over everything he did and they don't know how
What type of good monkey was they said is interior life. So what is the balance?
Yeah
So this is a great question because there's at least
At least three things in play here, right? There's the stuff that you say and think
as as one set okay
there
There's the stuff that you do, right?
The things that are apparent with your body,
although it should be argued by the way
that things you think are also bodily.
But for the sake of trying to understand
these as sort of sets, this is the way I'm gonna
assess it out.
And then there's what you're describing
as the interior life, okay?
So someone could be an accidental heretic
in the sense that they have an opinion.
that is wrong. And traditionally, while you could use the word heresy or heretic to refer
to that, traditionally, the kind of the strictest sense of what that means is someone who has
rejected the correction of the church, not just someone who has a wrong opinion. And
especially someone who's teaching that thing. So for instance, the anathema of the Ecumenical
Councils are-
make reference to those who teach XY and Z anathema, right? Not just those who
happen to think this or whatever, but those who are teaching it. So it's a very
deliberate, very sustained, very purposeful choice to go against the
correction of the church. Okay? So that is different from just what you happen to
think. And then also, I would say like what does the interior life actually
consist of. Okay?
Is it your opinions? Is it the thoughts that you have?
You know, by themselves in terms of like the traditional spiritual literature of the church,
when talking about the interior life, often the biggest thing that that is talking about is your prayer.
You know, the way that you pray especially privately, and the way that you repent especially privately.
Okay, so that is an action.
or set of actions really, right? And so then that's actually related then to
the things that you do. So that's why, for instance, the three traditional
disciplines of the church are prayer, fasting, and om's giving. These are things
that are both interior and exterior in terms of the way that they're aimed at
the world, right? But they are all exterior in the sense that they are all
things that you are doing with your body, right? The interior life is a thing
you're doing with your body.
Right? So that interiority is a different means something different than the interiority that we've been talking about in this episode in general, right?
Because it is something you do with your body. Like when you pray, that is you focusing, focusing your new sun God and, you know, probably praying with words,
unless you're really spiritually advanced and you can kind of get beyond that, which I'm not most people are not.
You know, so these are all actions that you take right?
So if someone has a wrong opinion,
and they never encounter correction from the church,
and so it never really becomes an issue,
does that make that opinion not matter?
No, of course it matters, but for them,
it probably doesn't matter very much.
Because if they're living a faithful life in the church,
even if they're kind of mistaken about something,
the point is that they were faithful.
Right.
Because again, you know, as I said, you know, there's a thousand.
in heresies every coffee hour.
People say stuff that's just really screwy.
For me, that's just one practitioner.
He knows who he is.
That's how from the heresies every coffee.
Yeah, and I mean, probably a lot of sermons
have heretical things that are being set
because the priest is just mistaken.
You know?
So yeah, it's not a, you know,
God's judgment.
on us is not a gotcha system. Okay? It's not. It's not. Like, I, you know, I have people in my life
who do not use language in the way that I do. Like, I try to be very precise with the way that I speak.
I still say things offhand. I still have verbal habits, etc. But I have people in my life that do not
use language in the way that I do. And it drives me insane. And they often say things that are literally
wrong, but I also know what they mean.
And I know what they're getting at, right?
And if I know what they're getting at through experience,
years of experience with these people,
how much more does God know what we're getting at,
who we really are?
You know, that maybe the way that we talk
and the way that we think is not really expressive of that.
So, does that make some sense, Bethany?
Yeah.
Father Steve.
Because I guess we could say that everything's
done with our bodies because thought.
being neural synapses, they're still exterior in a sense.
Yeah, in fact, I mean, traditionally,
the teaching is that thoughts come to us
from the outside.
Right, that's the key, right?
That's, we think of our mind as our brain,
which is in a box, sort of churning.
But the news is like a sensory organ.
Our mind is actually like a sensory organ.
Thoughts are external to it.
So we very easily identify the things that are I see
that are ears here.
or knows about those are as being external to us.
But because of our modern view of the mind,
we don't correctly identify thoughts as external to us.
Yeah, yeah, which is a little mind bending I know.
So, all right, does that help Bethany?
So what's the interior of your mind?
What do you think, Father?
How do we describe the interior?
I'll be...
I feel like there's been a lot of time, yeah, a lot of time saying that a whole it's not like
What can be said about it anything you might say about it would be an exterior kind of thing to say
You know
Yeah, right cuz like your soul doesn't take up space
Yeah, I'm right like
Yeah, I think we might say the soul but
But remember the soul's not a 7.
thing. It's not a thing in the world, right? It's, yeah, it's the life of the thing. So yeah,
that's what we mean by it. It's a little difficult to say, but that's what it is.
All right, well thank you for calling Bethany.
Great. Yeah, it's funny. I have to say that there's not a lot of people in the world named Bethany.
It's a relatively rare name, but one of them is my sister and this is not
my sister who called by the way everybody. My sister's not living Montana. As far as I'm aware.
You don't know where she is right now. Today, like I don't know where she doesn't call me.
It could be, you know, her whereabouts all the time. But yeah, so it creates a little weird
cognitive distance in its own head because to me, Bethany is the name attached to my sister.
I don't really actually don't know anybody currently in my life with that name. So anyway.
All right, we're going to take one more call and that's Judah. So Judah has a question about
the saint who rose from the dead when Jesus was crucified.
right? Judah, welcome to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
Hi, Father's bless. Can you hear me? God bless you. Yes, we hear you.
Awesome. Yeah. So I was looking through the Gospels and I remembered.
There might have been something you guys said in a previous episode, but there's this part where after
Jesus is crucified, um, it says that the saints came out of their graves and they went to the Holy City and
peer to many. Is there any sort of correlation between this bodily resurrection and
and the bodily resurrection that awaits the faithful
around or after the second coming.
That's a great question.
So yeah, as I say, Father, I've started,
I've entered all of the rest of them first.
Why don't you go ahead and be, you know,
unless you just wanna say yes.
That was it, I was just gonna say yes.
Yeah, that's it's in St. Matthew's Gospel.
And there's something even more interesting than that
because when Christ dies, they come to life.
but they don't emerge from their tombs until he does.
Yeah, that's what it says.
So if you want to take it wouldn't be literally,
in St. Matthew's Gospel, like they rose,
they sat around for two days and then came out of their tombs
and it appeared to people.
Right.
I would suggest that we not take it that wouldn't be literally.
It's weird enough without adding more weird.
Yeah, so
The idea behind that detail, I think, is the idea that the resurrection of Christ is the beginning of the general resurrection.
That's why they come out when Christ is raised.
And the fact that the phrase is they appeared to many also implies that something about that coming out of the tombs. It's not like they crawled up.
out of the ground and walked around covered in dirt
and the walking dead or something, right?
Cause they're appearing to people
that implies they're then sort of disappearing
and appearing to someone else sort of the way Christ did.
Right?
So I think what St. Matthew is doing there narratively
is what St. Paul is doing in Hebrews
when he says in Hebrews 11,
that the...
saints of the old covenant, the Old Testament, were not made perfect until with us.
So Christ's resurrection is sort of when they, on the whole, minus Moses,
Enic Elijah, experience the resurrection. And that's why you get them making
appearances similar to the appearances of Christ.
Hmm, right.
And so then like Christ's appearances after his bodily resurrection, those appearances would then be sort of a glimpse or a taste or the first fruits or a through line to the general resurrection when it comes.
Hmm.
I don't think I've ever heard it put that quite that way before.
Because I mean, like the sense that I think that it usually gets talked about.
and correct me from
wrong because I want to be correct on this is that there's a group of people who come
to life who are resuscitated like in the way that Lazarus was and that presumably die
again at some point. Right. No. I don't that's ignoring I think what St. Matthew actually
says. What he talks about them appearing to people. Yeah. Although there is. Now there is
nothing about them done
again and it's specifically you have to take into account that it's talking about the Old Testament
saints so it's talking about the righteous ones of the Old Testament. Right and you have to
understand that in the fair sayic tradition their way of saying somebody was a saint in our modern
terminology right one of the very common ways in the second temple period is that they will be
included in the resurrection of the debt.
Right.
That's what you say.
Daniel will surely be included
in the resurrection of the dead. Isaiah will surely be included in the resurrection of the
dead. Right. And so the idea is, right, remember, remember what Christ says in St. John's Gospel
to Martha, right? He says, do you believe in the resurrection of the dead? She says, yeah,
I believe on the last day, and Jesus says, I am the inocencies, right? Yeah. Jesus is the
inocencies. Yeah. So then being part of it is what I think St. Matthew is dramatizing.
That you got
I think that Jewish context.
It's interesting also, like, as I'm trying to put this
together in my head, I think about,
and obviously this is not a canonical text,
but like the Gospel of Nicodemus,
where the frame narrative is, there's these two sons
of Simeon who came out of their graves
and are living in some house somewhere.
And they bring them down to, in front of the Sanhedrin,
to tell what they saw in the underworld,
which is then re-
you get the whole hearing of Hades narrative.
But I think that that still works.
And within the frame that you're describing,
even though it's a lot more kind of literalized
in the sense of like they live in some house somewhere.
Well, that's also a narrative frame.
Yeah, yeah.
For the gospel of Nicotimus.
Yeah.
Yeah, yeah.
So anyway, well, that's interesting.
We must talk on this more.
I will hear more of this at some other time.
Yeah.
So.
All right.
I hope that that's helpful and useful to you.
Yeah, it certainly was definitely going to be something I'll have to poke around a bit more.
I'm going to be doing a semester at Holen at college in a little bit.
But before I go, I did want to briefly mention that my dad is the co-host of Bruce Beard and Shipwrecks with Jamie Bennett.
Oh, all right.
All right.
It's wise you said that before asking the question,
we might have just...
Oh!
I'm sorry.
Not because we have anything against you or your father,
just we don't want you to start wrapping.
It's true.
My dad loves boxes of the house all the time, actually.
Oh, I mean, I love Jamie Bennett,
but yeah, the wrapping thing just bucks me.
What can I say?
All right.
Well, thank you for calling, Judy.
And God be with you as you study up there on the Holy Hill
in Brookline, Massachusetts.
Two sets.
Welcome. Thank you again. Good bye.
Oh yeah.
All right.
It's the third half of Lord of
Spirits. Are there no more
collars on the line?
That's it. We're closer.
Down, man. Yeah. I'm sure.
Get one more.
Not even one more.
Yeah.
I mean, you just want to take.
I can actually, by the way,
this would be a good point to tell everybody.
Um, next, the next episode is not going to be in two weeks.
is gonna be in three weeks.
on the 29th of August and we're going to do an all Q&A episode. So, you know, we will
take all callers that night. So yeah, all of them all wipe them out. Yeah. So right.
So what is exactly is eternal life then if we're talking about the bodily resurrection,
It's not just about, you know, bodies coming up.
It's eternal lives.
So what is that?
What is that actually?
Right.
So as if what we've already gone through wasn't enough.
Right?
So before we go any further, let's synthesize the first two
halves of the episode, not of your look.
So in order for the bodily resurrection to...
be a bodily resurrection, meaning in order for the bodily resurrection to be your identity.
Well, I'll just say with Diagphothia and your damage, you the listener.
I wonder if that's somebody's, if your name is Hugh and you're a listener, just know I'm always talking about you and I say Hugh the listener.
I might have met that guy in Wales.
Okay.
So yeah
to be Hugh the listener,
for it to be him, right, who is alive again, right,
after having physically died,
that not only the web of relationships
in which we have lived and our actions,
right, need to be resurrected,
But the...
time, the time of our life needs to be resurrected or redeemed as it were. Yeah. All of that,
this life, the life we live in this world, we live a life that needs to be restored. And
And I know this is a little brain-straining, but...
This is actually how at least significant portions of the New Testament talk about eternal life because
a lot of us hear eternal life, right, or life of the age, if we want to be pedantic or we've read a lot of D.B.H.
Right? As we talked about last time, you can have the life of the age to come and the age to come can have no end.
But even when we say
that right we say the life of the age of comas no end. The way you may hear that
and the way a lot of times we traditionally think about that is okay. I'm going to die.
There's going to be the intermediate state right then the bodily resurrection will happen.
I'll be alive in the body again and then there will be just an endless succession of moments.
Yeah, they'll just go on and on.
time will go on pretty much like it is now, but it'll go on forever. And that's what
eternal means. Right, in this case, right, eternal just means that that one, this one,
comes to an end, that one won't, right? And it's good that this one comes to an end,
because there's all this bad stuff in the world, but that one there will just be good stuff
of the world. So it'll go on forever with just good stuff.
That's sort of problematic for a bunch of reasons.
Watch the good place, if you want to know some of them.
Right.
But most importantly, that's not how a lot of, as I was just saying,
the New Testament scriptures actually talk about it.
So the way particularly, there's a particular pronounce
in the Johanian literature, meaning the stuff written by St. John.
That's in the New Testament.
that eternality
is an adjective, is a quality that is applied to our life.
Right? Not just sort of to our solar, to our life force or something,
but to the actual life that we live in this world.
Yes, so it's not just something in the future.
Right. The life we live in this world that's already going on,
This life.
already in progress, right? Has eternality applied to it through the resurrection of Christ?
Takes on this quality that it didn't previously have. Is transformed or transfigured in some way
such that it now possesses that quality. Right? And so a good example of
of eternal life being talked about.
this way is in 1 John 5 11 through 13.
Okay.
Yeah.
It goes this way.
And this is the testimony that God gave us any eternal life.
And this life is in His Son.
Whoever has the Son has life, whoever does not have the Son of God does not have life.
I write these things to you who believe in the name of the Son of God that you may know
that you have any eternal life.
Now, you may have noticed if you're falling along in your Bibles, because you're really
good at sword drills and you were able to look it up that fast.
Sword drills.
That Father Andrew added an indefinite article at a couple of points, meaning instead of
just saying that you may know that you have eternal life, he said you may have an eternal
life.
There's a reason for that.
It's that
the adjective,
eternal when it's applied to life,
then the New Testament, especially the Johanian literature, is always an
arthoris and is always indefinite.
That's why there's an indefinite article, right?
So it is correct to read it in English in that way that you have been given
and eternal life. Right? You live a life that life.
has taken on this capacity of eternality.
Now, again, I know this is kind of brain bending.
How can, because my life in this world
had a beginning and will have an end, right?
So how can this life be transformed and transfigured
and become eternal, right?
What we talked about and showed in the first two halves
is
This life in this world being transformed and becoming eternal is exactly what our body being resurrected to eternal life means
Right because if it isn't our life in this world that's resurrected and transfigured and made eternal then it's not us in terms of identity
Right, it's not us in terms of identity at that point
We'd be talking about becoming someone else
Who's not us?
fundamental ways. We're going to go more into this. Right? We're not leaving
the figure. I know this is kind of tricky to understand. But if you've read
much in orthodox theology, right? Both patristic and sense, especially things
talking about fiosis. Right? You may...
They have run across different authors, both, you know, later theologians, saints, church
fathers, using terminology like talking about people in salvation, in theosis, becoming
uncreated or becoming unbegotten.
Which sounds completely weird because humans are created and we're definitely be gotten.
Yes.
That sounds bizarre.
Like we, you know, right?
Yeah.
Yeah. But right, I think if we if we start to get a handle on this way of thinking about eternal life,
those kind of terms make sense. Right. That our life in this world, our actual life,
or actually, I didn't know that that is transfigured and made eternal. Then while it still sounds a
little wonky. You can understand
what it would mean because if something is truly eternal, the way we talked about God's
eternity last time, right, which is not just an endless succession of moments, right?
Then that makes sense of this unbegotten or uncreated language.
That language is somewhat awkward to us pointer to the kind of thing that we're talking about
right now.
But now, right, if you're tracking, if you've kind of got your head around what we're
talking about. A question that might be occurring to you is, um, okay, so again, anybody
listening who's able to routinely call in at least is still alive, their life of this
world is not done, right? It's, it's in progress. Um, but you're probably already looking
back at various points in your life and things that have happened and said, well, I definitely
don't want that part to become it.
eternal. Yeah, right? Like they're probably you can think of moments and times in your
life that you would love to be eternal. You would love them if those moments and those times
in the relationships you shared, including your relationship with God, right? Maybe especially
your relationship with God. If those moments and stuff, if those became eternal, that's heaven,
Right?
Totally down with that, but there are probably also moments in your life where you're like if that became eternal that would be hell
Yeah
Right that would be hell if that became eternal
And so
We have to remember that
right
What we get from the fathers
Right is that
After the end of this life, there is a pure f-
that happens. And the problem is, right, that I think at least us contemporary English speaking folks have kind of lacked the language to really explain what that means in Orthodox circles.
So, again, just like we were talking about with the problematic way of understanding eternal
life, I think, frankly, and again, I know this is going to get some of our Roman Catholic listeners.
mad at me because of course I will be misrepresenting them. I'm sure for some of them, no matter
what I say. I think that the understanding of purgatory is an over-literalization of
what this purification means in the same way that thinking of eternal life as an endless
This succession of positive moments is an oversimplification of what eternal life means.
I-E.
the idea of purgatory as purification, right, is that the individual person, the individual
human soul, because this happens while you don't have a body, has to be, again, this ties
identity to the soul, which is already a problem we talked about in the first half, right?
That's assumed here, that your identity, including your sinfulness, everything, your actions,
are all qualities of your soul, not your body,
otherwise purgatory doesn't work prior to the resurrection,
which is where it's set forth.
And that there is some kind of process
that is consistently described
throughout medieval Roman Catholic literature
as temporal, as taking place over time.
Sometimes very woody literally, people are given...
Indole.
literal time off purgatory. I understand that now modern Roman Catholic
doctors stuff says that purgatory is more of a metaphor. It's not a place, etc.
I am aware of all that, okay. But I don't see how those dovetail because you
still have the prayers to get people quote unquote time off purgatory. So I
appreciate wanting to understand it in a more analogical way. That's better, but
There's big holes in your analogy.
If you're going to say it's not temporal, then how can you get time off?
How do indulgences work vis-a-vis that?
I'm not a Roman Catholic, that's not for me to figure out. You guys figure that out.
But it's on this individual basis and in this at least quasi-literalized way.
way, right? But so, and of course the orthodox church has steadfast.
steadfastly rejected purgatory as such, I think for these reasons, while still continuing
to talk about purification after death. And I think that, again, the understanding that
we're laying out, the way of thing we're laying out to help us understand it, because if
what is being made eternal, if what is being raised, if what is being transfigured is
Our actual life across time and space lived in the world, across our life.
Right then what is going to be purified is not our soul is
Not the snapshot of who we are at the moment we died
that person
But what's gonna have to be purified
Before it's made eternal is our whole life across time and space. Okay, so I have a question and this is a real question because
There is a lot like everything you just said makes sense to me
But there is a lot of language in our
himnography and so forth.
that talks about the salvation of our souls. Or for instance, you know, like, in fact, the
Appolitechian for Samary of Egypt, you know, she taught us to attend to the soul since it is immortal.
Yes. You know, like, you have all of this kind of stuff. So like, what does that mean in this
framework? Yes. It means our life. Okay. Okay. Okay. It does not mean the soul in terms of the
animating for us because how what would that mean?
Yeah, yeah, this is the soul in terms of an atom became a living soul.
Right. Right. Yeah.
So if we're talking about take care of it as a thing, right?
What I mean, what does that mean? Yeah. Yeah.
I mean, that's the thing is like there's so there's some ambiguity in the language.
Right. We're so used to hearing soul and thinking of it as a thing.
Yeah. Right.
You have this thing take care of it.
Well, how do you take care of a...
So, yeah, but you can take care of your life.
Right.
Yeah.
You can create, you can garden, you can write all kinds of different things.
Well, and actually, you know, it's interesting.
I think that life, at least in English, kind of does this, covers this semantic range because we talk about life in terms of like,
Well my whole life I right and that's the life that we're talking about that's that that's so in terms of the this all you attend to
right? But then we also talk about like the life, you know, he's alive right now, you know,
the life in the body, right? So, so yeah, it has this semantic range. So this shouldn't be too hard
for everybody, right? Because we are in this way. What is it profit a man to gain the whole world and
lose his soul? Right? That doesn't mean it. If you think your soul is like your spleen, that doesn't make
He says, right.
It's this constituent part of you.
Right.
like it's your life, right?
He's making the point that proverbs makes, right?
You accumulate all this wealth and then you die.
Right.
Yeah.
Right?
Okay.
All right.
But so I thought that was an important clarification
to make up here.
Yeah.
So the purification we're talking about that comes out of that
is the purification of your whole life across time space
All of this has to be pure.
right? Has to be purified. And I think it's this that, for example, the famous
purification passage in 1 Corinthians 3 11 through 15 is talking about. Yeah, yeah. So in case.
The whole life. In case you just can't, you know, quote, in case you don't know which verses
these are, it's this one. It should be very familiar to you. You've heard it. For no one
can lay a foundation other than that which is laid, which is Jesus Christ. Now, if anyone builds
on the f**k.
with gold silver precious stones, wood hay straw,
each one's work will become manifest for the day will disclose it,
because it will be revealed by fire.
And the fire will test what sort of work each one has done.
If the work that anyone is built on the foundation survives,
he will receive a reward.
If anyone's work is burned up, he will suffer loss,
though he himself will be saved, but only as through fire.
fire. Yes.
So, this is not talking about like some kind of merits you've built up in your life.
No, and it should be stated that if someone has the foundation of Jesus Christ, that means
he is a Christian.
Like, this is about Christians.
Yeah.
Right.
And this is, but this is talking about the purification of your life.
Right?
And that is determined by what as we've been talking about.
as determined by what you do.
that's shaping your identity. So this purification is like the purification of
metal. That's what's used mostly in the Hebrew scriptures. St. Paul here is
using metal and gems because those don't burn either. You subject it to
incredible heat, you smelt it, that's unpleasant, but it removes all the
the impurities.
And you're left with
the pure in the good. Okay? So apply this to what we're talking about. Right. So this, and again,
this is a way of thinking. This is not, I don't even know what it would mean for this to be literal,
but this is a way of thinking about it. And we should say it's, it's a way of thinking. It's not
the only way, right? Right. It's a way, and it is a way that I think as we've already shown,
and we'll continue to show in the rest of this half.
It helps make certain things that the fathers and stuff say intelligible, more intelligible
than other ways of thinking about it.
Right?
And so it's a helpful way of thinking about it, a useful way of thinking about it.
So if we think about this as, right, some the day will come, I will die physically.
My soul will leave my body.
Then, right.
And we've done...
about the intermediate state before, but then the day with capital D will come and I will stand
before the judgment seat of Christ. And in that judgment, my life, my actual life, the life that
I lived in the world, which constitutes who I am, all my actions spread out across time,
all of my relationships, all of those things get subjected to fire.
And all of the garbage, all of the sin, all of the evil, all of the suffering, all of
the pain, all of that gets burned away.
And then what is left, what is left, those parts of my life, however many are few, ever
great or small that remain after.
that. Right? Those moments where during my life, that those times when during my life, those
spaces and relationships and connections which during my life were permeated by the
divine energies, the energies of God by God's love, His joy, His peace. Right? Those moments
will also be permeated by his eternity.
And they'll be made eternal.
And I will dwell within them eternally.
Okay, this is a way of thinking.
And so, within this way of thinking about it,
if someone says, well, what about all those painful moments
and those horrible experiences? Right?
Because some of them as we've already talked about, right?
are repentance may have shaped our identity and that repentance required sin. Right?
Right. What would happen to those things that are burned away, is the way of thinking about it
phenomenologically, is that there would be a kind of forgetting rather than an eternal memory.
That those are things that would be forgotten.
Right?
And you can keep the fruit of those things without keeping those things.
A rose, most roses grow out of thorn bushes. Right?
But once they've grown, you can pluck them from the thorn bush.
You can burn the thorn bush if you want to at that point. Right?
and just keep the roses.
Right. So those good things, those aspects of our identity that are good and godly, that
came out of suffering, that came out of us needing to find deep repentance for sin.
After the fact that sin can be burned away, that suffering can fall into forgetfulness.
Right.
But the good fruit that came out of that can remain.
as part of our identity and who we are eternally.
So this is what we're getting at.
We're talking about the love, the joy, the peace, all of these things of this life.
Those things becoming eternal, the rest going away.
It's not just an ongoing succession into the future of nice moments,
but it's in the ha-
the sacred moments of our life eternally, and so that what that means is, right?
And what's they call us getting at in 1 Corinthians 3 in this understanding, is that our goal in
living this life and living our Christian life in this world is to multiply and extend those moments
and to begin already to burn away and repent of and forget the others.
So the life of a saint is a life that was filled with the love of God, the joy that comes
from God, the peace of God.
And the person who St. Paul describes as being saved by fire is someone who lived a life
that maybe, you know, wasn't so permeated.
Yeah, and there were many diseases.
Right. There is the language in the New Testament of those who are greater and those who are less in the kingdom of heaven.
You know, they're in the kingdom, but some are greater and some are lesser.
Right. Right.
And so within this, right, any eventual hell after the last judgment would be a hell of one's own making.
As we mentioned to the caller, it would come from a persistent and continual
rejection
Right of
The grace of God which is God's actions of his love of his joy of his peace throughout an entire life
Yeah, and it's not again. It's not like oh you messed up. So bam, you know
Right no a constant rejection through a whole life, right?
And so now we turn to the onion story.
Which is an old Russian folk tale, but you can find it in Dostoyevsky.
Yes.
If you can get farther into Brother's Karmazov, then Father Andrew did.
That's right.
I always quit after the first 1500 pages.
Or so, I can't, you know.
So, this is a story.
recounted of there is an old woman living in a village who was just a miserable old woman.
She was angry, she was bitter, she never had a kind word for anyone, she was rude,
lived alone, didn't want anyone near her, right, completely curmudgeonly.
like, uh, uh, uh, said a horror.
things to people and the day comes and she dies. And so some of the people in her village being
good Christian people go to their village priest, they start having memorial services for her,
they start praying for her soul. Right, they say this miserable woman definitely needs our prayers
for her soul. That's how they respond to her wickedness and her addict.
and so God hears their prayers and this is a folk teller.
And so he assigns an angel sort of to her case right to see sort of what can be
what can be done with this woman who is now in Hades and the angel sort of
reviews her life, the life that she lived.
And out of all of it, he only finds this one thing that he thinks maybe he can work with.
There was this one time when she was walking home from the market,
and she saw someone who was hungry and in need, and she gave them an onion.
So she did this one kind of nice charitable act once in her life.
And that's pretty much it.
So the angel goes to Hades with the onion.
Right, that you...
gave to this person. And he reached out, he extends the onion toward her. She takes hold
of the onion. He begins to pull her up out of Hades by the onion. And then suddenly the
old woman yells, give me my onion and yanks it away from the angel and falls back at the
Hades. I hope you weren't expecting a happy ending to a Russian folktale. Because if
so you're parking up the wrong tree.
Oh man.
Deacon Nichol...
this co-tars entered the chat.
Anyway, so that's a little dark, right?
But this is your hypothetical worst-case scenario.
But the idea that's reflected in that folktale
is the same kind of idea we're getting at tonight.
So this woman is sort of your worst-case scenario,
in terms of rejecting the love of God
the love of
neighbor and everything else, right? But there's this one moment, right? And if she sort
of had followed through with that one moment, that one moment where she showed love to her
neighbor, if she had followed through on that, she could have found salvation, right? And
not just salvation in some kind of broad sense, but this is directly in this folktale, in
the sense of eternal life. Right? That one moment.
of love and kindness could have become an eternal moment that she could dwell in with God for eternity,
but she rejected that too. But she rejects that too. So as I said, hopefully from this, you've
We've got kind of an idea of this way of thinking about bodily resurrection eternal life.
that we've been getting at.
That I've been teasing that we've already seen some,
but I will give you a few more here,
ways in which I think this way of thinking about it is helpful.
I think this view helps where a lot of our contemporary views
are problematic.
I mean, those common contemporary view of this
It doesn't even talk about the bodily resurrection.
Right. You go to the average person on the street who's religious or who even identifies
as a Christian and you say, what happens to you and you die, they're going to say, well,
probably in the US, Christians go to heaven and other people go to hell. Right. Yeah.
Or good people go to heaven. Or good people go to heaven. If they're, yeah, especially
if they don't identify as Christian, they'll say, good people go to heaven, bad people go
hell. There's nothing about the bodily resurrection even in there, right?
Yeah.
So that's obviously problematic.
But even a lot of views of the bodily resurrection are like we said, you know, we'll be back alive
and I guess doing stuff forever, singing or something.
It's not totally clear what people think that will be.
And I think this obviously, this way of thinking about gets passed.
Those kind of problems.
But I think more importantly, this explains a lot of the language of Scripture, the analogies that are used.
About the life of the world to come, we've looked at a couple of them.
But one of the problems, for example, in the early church,
What are the main problems with kiliasim in the early church was that people tended
Because we see this getting condemned all over the place. People tended to think of
Paradise and of the life of the world's coming eternal life as being sort of a garden of earthly delights. Yeah
You know, you're gonna get to drink buckets of wine and eat all this good food and
And do all this stuff, right?
But let me suggest something here
Why would they go wrong in that particular way?
Right. Like there's no danger. Your average American who you ask, they say, well, you go to
heaven or hell when you die. There's no danger of them picturing heaven or hell. Well,
definitely not hell, but picturing heaven is sort of a garden of earthly delights where
you're eating and drinking and feasting all the time. Right. That all. Right. Well, it seems
me that the way you would go wrong in that way would be if the way
people were describing eternal life was in terms of this life. Becoming eternal, right?
Of the good and sacred moments of this life becoming eternal. If you're talking about it that way,
then you could see how someone was a little confused. We're going to say, oh yeah, all the cool stuff I
I love that this life is going to become eternal.
Right. Right. It's going to be like Baldur's Gate 3.
but I'm not gonna finish after a hundred hours, right?
Like, and all the bad stuff won't be in there.
Yeah, frozen yogurt, anyway.
Right, so you could see someone going wrong in that way,
if what's being preached to them
has to do with life in this world.
And this life's becoming eternal,
then going wrong in that way
in the early church makes a lot of sense.
I'm needing to be.
correct it. This explains the eternal life and eternal death language that's used
by the Scriptures. You know, we'll get the annihilationist folks who will say like,
oh see eternal death, that means you cease to exist forever. It's like wait a minute, wait a minute,
wait a minute. Since what does death mean ceasing to exist? Right. Right. I mean, if you're,
if you're going to take eternal death literally, that would mean your soul says separated from your
your body forever.
Not that it ceases to exist.
Yeah, which in the intermediate state forever.
Yeah, right.
Right, which is explicitly not what the scripture says.
There's going to be a bottomer as a lecture.
Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah. And not what an dialect just argue for.
So that kind of argument that dog don't hunt that maybe even worse than the open
Theus thing, but maybe not.
I don't know.
So you got to book in things.
Um
This also means that talking about, for example, earning eternal life makes absolutely no sense.
Hmm. Right. There's no way to bring earning or merit or any of that earning salvation.
There's no way to bring any of that in, right? That like, that's not a paradigm that fits with this
way of thinking at all.
Because how could you do that?
Yeah.
Right.
I don't think that just, it doesn't make sense, right?
In this way of thinking.
It also makes, if you've read much from orthodox sources on this, when orthodox sources talk
about eternal condemnation because orthodox sources are not universalist, when they talk
about eternal condemnation, they don't talk about, quote unquote, eternal conscious, conscious
torment.
We've gone into that before.
or on the show, why all three of those words don't mean what they think they mean.
But that's not ever how the Orthodox Church expresses what eternal condemnation is.
The most common thing that gets talked about in those discussions from Orthodox sources
is that eternal condemnation has to do with a diminution or loss of humanity.
It's kind of a subhumanness and you even have the language of becoming truly human to
refer to salvation.
Right, the salvation.
in crisis to be in crisis become truly human.
And so then the opposite of that is to have your humanity
dimension. That language makes a whole lot of sense with this
way of thinking about eternal life. Right. If everything
about your human life is burned away and you're left with
nothing. Right. Then the diminution or loss of your
humanity.
as a way of speaking in a metaphor makes a whole lot of sense.
Right?
Whereas it's just kind of vague otherwise.
I'm not saying this is the only way of thinking about it where that makes sense, but this
is a way of thinking about it where that makes a lot of sense.
Yeah.
Were these things kind of fit together around this way of thinking about it?
Yeah, and it occurs to me like that sense that this is not urnable, right?
I think I don't know.
that would work or like as similarly as probably the right word, yes.
It's like saying that being in good health is earnable.
Like if you work out, you know, like if you work out a lot that earns you good health.
It doesn't.
Like, you know, not buying it by doing a thing.
You can still die of a heart attack from a heart defect.
You don't know.
That's right.
But, you know, it's really about changing and transforming and training.
you know, that's that's
where why it takes you there.
It's not like, okay, if I spend this amount of time
at the gym, then I get this.
No, no, that's not how that works.
Yeah, there's no quid pro quo.
Yeah.
But to me, at least the most important part
and what set me down this path of thinking this through
and thinking this way aside from Nietzsche.
I'd know I won't go into that any further.
Oh, if nature couldn't teach you.
You had to go to PazzoFest to know more about that angle.
But to me the most important thing was to put in a result of thinking about it in this
way.
And in the six months or so since PazzoFest I've been thinking about it more is that this
firmly places the emphasis.
of the Christian life on this life that we live here in this world. There's a common characterization
of Christian belief that to a certain extent is a straw man used by your local internet
atheist.
But it's a straw man when you're talking about, so this is always one of the problems, right?
This is a straw man, if you're talking about sort of the great tradition of Christian theology.
In terms of what the average person who identifies as a Christian believes, it's probably not a straw man.
Right. So one way to construct a straw man is to select the worst representatives of your opponent.
Right, sort of the ones who have actually thought about it the least, right?
Or the ones that say the least supportable things and use them as an example of the whole.
That's one way to construct a straw man argument.
And so then you defeat that claim, you've defeated the whole.
But that's that Christianity because of this emphasis on a quote unquote afterlife,
or the life of the world to come or heaven or however it's expressed.
big
Because of that, it is by nature
an otherworldly religion and therefore minimizes
the importance of our life in this world
and the things we do in this world
and taking care of this world
or caring for people or caring about injustice
in this world, et cetera, et cetera, et cetera.
Right?
And like I said, in terms of the great tradition
of Christian theology, in terms of the scriptures,
in terms of that, that's a straw man.
But in terms of a lot of people walking around
calling themselves Christians and how they think and act.
Not really a straw man, right?
That kind of fits, right?
Kind of fits.
It's easy to fall into this idea of especially when,
especially when there are certain types,
especially of Protestant Christianity
that put this enormous stress on the idea
of assurance of salvation, right?
Make it a linchpin, right?
They'll say like, well, no, I accept this theology
and up.
that theology because this theology gives me assurance of salvation. Now there's a certain irony there.
Right. Even that, well okay, that theology, if it's true, gives you assurance of salvation,
but how do you know it's true? Right. Right. Like, because I like it. There's an issue there. Right.
Because I want to have insurance of my salvation. But placing the emphasis there on your own personal
assurance that you are saved. Has this kind of rip?
effect. And that ripple effect is that then in this life my goal is okay whatever the things are I
need to do what must I do to be saved right whatever those things are right whether it's just believe
whether it's believe and be baptized whether it's believe and receive the sacrifice of the church
whether it's whatever else we want to put in there right believe and accumulate merit through good
it works.
whatever you want to put in there, right?
If your focus is on assurance, then the way you're going to look at life is,
okay, I get those things squared away and then do whatever.
Right? Get wealthy, enjoy good things.
I do whatever. As long as I got that after I die, things squared away were good.
Right? That is a temptation into which a lot of people fall.
But if we think about eternal life in this way, right, that's precluded.
Right?
That's precluded.
Because the life of the world to come, eternal life, the life that's going to be eternal
is this life.
Right?
And if this life is going to be our eternity, then our whole focus in this life should
be transforming our life in this world.
transforming who we are, transforming our identity in Christ.
Through repentance, through participating in God's love, His joy, His peace by being a peacemaker,
all of these things, that is what the focus of our whole life here will become, because we want
all of those things in our life that we can possibly get, because we want to spend eternity there.
right in those things.
And I
I think refocusing our Christian lives on our Christian lives in this world with the
people in our world, with the things in our world, over the course of the time we have
in this world is the most important thing.
And you know, I think I just kind of gave my final thought.
So I will let you give your...
final thought father Andrew that we could just wrap up.
Wow.
I don't know what to say about that.
I'm breaking the format.
I don't care.
I know.
You're just yeah.
Maddo control.
He is a wild one folks.
Yeah so I know some people are probably thinking like wait a minute.
I'm thinking of do a transfiguration episode.
to be.
too late to do it later.
And although this episode was not aimed at the feast
of the Transfiguration and kind of working through all that,
we have in many cases, we have made reference
to those events on many occasions.
But I do want to talk about the Transfiguration a little bit
because it shows us some of what's going on here
in terms of what.
the resurrection of the body means.
Right?
So the Lord Jesus Christ,
standing on Mount Tabar,
Peter, James, and John going up there with him,
and the prophets Moses and Elias appear there with him,
and they're speaking with him.
And I think the thing that a lot of people come away from the scene with,
and this is correct,
that this is not wrong is, you know, when Jesus transph...
He shines from his body.
This shows that he's God, right?
And certainly like this is reflected in the the hemnography of the feast, you know, that
in fact, he explicitly says that that Peter James and John see this and so that so that
when he's crucified, they would know it was voluntary.
Like, you know, look, he's God.
Okay.
So when he's crucified, it's voluntary.
No one did that to him in the sense of like they over
power day. And of course, Christ himself says, no one takes my life from me. I lay it down
if I own a court. Right. So that is true. But also what we're seeing there with the two
prophets who are with him, one of whom is taken up into heaven, even while still living
in the body. Then that's Elias. And then of course, the prophet Moses, we get that reference
about his body being ticked.
up because there's this you know fight over his body between the Archangel Michael and the devil.
As I mentioned in the New Testament, that they're both participating maybe in different ways,
hard for me to know at this point in this life, but they're both participating in the bodily resurrection.
And while we can't say exactly what that's like because not just the bad thing, but you know,
whatever.
There are some indications.
We do have, as we've mentioned many, many times in this podcast, Christ saying that the
Sun's the Resurrection, the Sun's of God, equals the angels, right?
So that's since that they function in an angelic way.
So clearly there's, their bodies are less limited than human bodies are in this life that
we're experiencing now.
There is more importantly a communion with Christ, a vision of Christ and glory that they're
experiencing.
I mean, in the epistle reading that is for the feast from St. Peter's second epistle,
when he talks about the transfiguration that he saw that he witnessed himself, he says
he opens up that passage by saying that it's about our entrance into the kingdom of God.
And he wants to...
remind us of this so that we can be faithful,
so that we can make that entrance
into the kingdom of God.
Right?
And it's interesting that he wouldn't say,
now, like, make sure you're good
so that you can go to heaven when you die, whatever.
But instead, he says,
I want to remind you of this thing that we saw,
and it's about the kingdom of God,
that Christ as God ascended on the mountain,
ascended on the mountain which becomes as St Peter said.
in that passage the holy mountain, right, it becomes the holy mountain. This is the life of the
age to come. This is another way of understanding the life of the age to come. And so this vision of
Christ and glory is given to Peter James and John and he tells us about it. He's an eyewitness. We
receive his witness so that we can be faithful so that we can know what we're moving towards.
Because as Father just said, the life of the age to come
is not just an endless series of moments,
and it's not just even an endless series of moments
in which good things are happening
and no bad thing ever happens.
No, no, no.
It is of a much higher order
than even the best possible moments
that we can imagine in this life.
And that's expressed in what happens in the transfiguration.
Right?
That is what the Kingdom of God looks like,
or it's one way of understanding the Kingdom of God.
Okay.
As we know, Christ gives a number, Christ Himself gives a number of different images for
the Kingdom of God.
It's like this, the Kingdom of God is like this, but also the Kingdom of God is very much
like this.
It's like what happens on the table, right?
And that the destiny of mankind in Christ is to be having the experience that Moses and
Elias are having there with him, experiencing the resurrection, communing with the glorified
Christ in His human body.
Right? When he's transfigured, his human body doesn't disappear and then they just see this blinding light.
No, they see it coming from his human body.
You know? So in a sense, a lot of this is about the transfiguration.
Not just that one event that happens that we find in the gospels, but about
what that tells us about the kingdom of God,
what that tells us about...
Christ in glory, what that tells us about the scenes in Christ's glory, that they have,
as Christ himself prayed for in his great high priestly prayer, that the glory that
God the Father gave to him, that he gives them that glory.
That's not a metaphor.
That's a reality.
And the transfiguration shows us what that reality looks like from a particular angle.
And so what you do with that is...
You keep that in front of you, just like St. Paul says, I press towards
the mark of the high calling of God.
This is the high calling he's talking about.
It's no coincidence that he uses the word high to refer to it.
That it is this ascent.
Again, we made reference to the latter of divine ascent.
It's this ascension.
Now in this life, as we mentioned, some ascensions, some stumbling back.
But nonetheless, the
Christian life is about this ascension up the mountain.
And it's not just to reach some point of greatness,
but it is that divine counsel of communion with God,
of becoming sons of God, of becoming part of his royal family,
that all the good that is our life in this life.
that doesn't just continue but becomes elevated and glorified and magnified and has the character
of eternality about it. And that should give us a lot of hope, a lot to be grateful for, a lot to
keep us steady in times of difficulty. Not just this is in the future sometime but also this is now
And so
Every moment of goodness now is eternal.
That's really amazing to think about.
That every moment of communion, every moment of love, every moment of faithfulness, all
of this participates in Christ and therefore is eternal.
difficult to understand.
But it...
It is, I believe, profoundly comforting, not just in the sense of, okay, everything's
gonna be okay, but rather that it lifts us up and gives us this high hope so that we can
always be pressing forward throughout our lives.
So that's what I have to say about all that.
Thank you very much everyone for listening.
That is our show for tonight.
If you didn't happen to get through to us live this time around, we'd like to hear from
and you can email us at Lord of Spirit, St. John.
You can message our Facebook page, of course Facebook isn't real, but you can also leave
us a voice mail at speakpipe.com slash Lord of Spirits.
And if you have basic questions about Orthodox Christianity or you need help to find a
parish, go to Orthodoxintro.org.
And join us for our live broadcast on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 7 p.m.
Eastern 4 p.m. Pacific.
It's a cool place.
They say it gets colder.
You're bundled up now.
Wait till you get older.
If you're on Facebook, follow our page, join our discussion group.
and leave a rating somewhere, reviews.
But most importantly, please share this show with your friends
and have a discussion group with them about it at your parish.
And finally, be sure to go to www.infraith.com.stokesupport.
And help make sure we and lots of other AFR
podcasters stay on the air.
The media are meant to differ judging by
the whole in the satellite picture.
Thank you.
Good night and God bless you.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew
Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young, a listener-supported presentation of ancient
faith radio.
And I beheld, and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne and the beasts
and the elders.
And the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000, and thousands of thousands, saying with
the loud voice, worthy as the land that was slain to receive power.
riches and wisdom and strength and honor and glory and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses